<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations upon the warre of Hungary</title>
            <author>Littleton, Edward, b. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11871305</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11871305</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48744)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 501:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations upon the warre of Hungary</title>
                  <author>Littleton, Edward, b. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Randall Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Littleton, of All Souls'. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  History, Military.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OBSERVATIONS UPON THE WARRE OF HUNGARY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Randall Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall;</hi> and <hi>Tho. Newborough,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church Yard. 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:50124:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50124:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THeſe Obſervations were written, ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Things were done: that is, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the latter end of that Winter, which followed the Taking of <hi>Newhauſel.</hi> And they have now loſt much of their Reliſh: in regard the Actions are leſs freſh in memory, and the <hi>Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> of later Events and Accidents have taken poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Mens Minds. But the delay could not be avoided. For in the late Reign they would by no means be ſuffer'd to be Printed. though they had been ſeverely Garbled by ſome Friends; and though they were ſubmitted to any further Expurgations; and laſtly though nothing could be Objected, againſt the truth of the Matters here deliver'd. However there were ſeveral Written Copies went abroad. Some whereof were peruſed by the moſt Eminent in the late Court, and particularly by the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour. Who freely declared, that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with the Author in every point. But you
<pb facs="tcp:50124:3"/>may imagine, thoſe paſſages were then ſtruck out, which ſeemed to touch too hard upon his Maſter the <hi>French</hi> King; or that Kings Maſters, the Jeſuites.</p>
            <p>Perhaps it may ſeem preſumptuous, to give any Judgment of the Actions of great Men. But the thing well conſider'd, it is no more then what every body does. Every body does that in Diſcourſe, which is here done in Writing: that is, He ſays what he thinks, of ſuch Occurrences as he reads or hears of. They that have the Glory to appear pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in the Eyes of Mankind, do at the ſame time come under their Judgment. and as in the common Stages, ſo in the Grand Theater of the VVorld, the moſt principal and greateſt Actors muſt undergo the Cenſure, even of the meaneſt and moſt unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Spectators.</p>
            <p>You will ſay; We cannot give a Judgment of thoſe Actions, of which we do not know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But if this hold good, none can judge of Actions, ſave only They that deſigned them: for They only have a full knowledge of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And at this rate, the Lookers on may not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the play of the moſt bungling Gameſter. Alſo it would hence follow, that all Actions muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed alike, and we muſt give an implicit appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation
<pb facs="tcp:50124:3"/>of every thing that's done. So that our Expedition to the Iſle of <hi>Rè,</hi> which (as ſome think) had as many Errors as Actions, muſt be thought a piece of as good Conduct, as the Conqueſt of <hi>Egypt</hi> by Sultan <hi>Selim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we do well know that very famous Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are noted and confeſt to have had their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes. I forbear to enlarge upon this Subject (which it were eaſie to do) and ſhall inſtance only in <hi>Pompey:</hi> who was one of the greateſt Captains that the World hath known. <hi>Caeſar</hi> obſerves, that he acted unskilfully in the Battel of <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> when he order'd his Men to ſtand their ground, and receive their Enemies Charge. whereas plainly it adds Courage to the Soldier, to be in motion and advancing upon the Enemy. But <hi>Tully</hi> (who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to judge of few things which he did not well underſtand) condemns <hi>Pompey</hi> for fighting at all. <hi>Signa tirone &amp; collectitio Exercitu cum Legionibus robuſtiſſimis contulit.</hi> And he tells us what led him into that Error. <hi>Quadam ex Pugnâ</hi> (that of <hi>Dyrrhachium</hi> he means) <hi>coepit ſuis militibus confidere.</hi> And then he adds; <hi>Ex eo tempore Vir ille ſummus, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Imperator fuit.</hi> There was yet a greater Error, though no notice be taken of it, which
<pb facs="tcp:50124:4"/>
               <hi>Pompey</hi> committed in this Affair. And that was; That he ſtaid at all in <hi>Greece,</hi> after that <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his Army were got thither. There he ſtaid, as if he had been tied by ſome Charme, to be bearded, and beſieged, and at laſt beaten; when, being Maſter at Sea, and his whole Naval Force being come to him, he might with the greateſt eaſe have croſt over into <hi>Italy,</hi> and have ſhut <hi>Caeſar</hi> out of it. And nothing could then hinder his March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Rome:</hi> where he might have had his full Revenge upon the adverſe Faction. Which was the thing he long'd after. For the ſame <hi>Tully</hi> writes of him; <hi>Animus ejus Sullaturit &amp; Proſcripturit jam diu.</hi> He that would know the Intrigues of thoſe Affairs, muſt read <hi>Tully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt beg pardon of the Illuſtrious Heroe of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> if his Conduct ſometimes hath not been underſtood. But this may be ſaid in his Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion once for all; that there is great reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that he was too often bound up by ſtrict Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. The giving of which ſort of Orders is a thing that hath been always condemn'd, and will be always practis'd. It is a fine thing to ſit contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a Cabinet, and cutting out work for thoſe that muſt undergo the labour and the danger. But if Princes will have their work well done, (with
<pb facs="tcp:50124:4"/>the loweſt Submiſſion be it ſpoken); they ſhould either go themſelves, or truſt thoſe they ſend. If ever any Council were qualified to manage Wars by particular Orders, it was the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate: which was compoſed, for the moſt part, of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that had been in high Command. it was in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a Council or Aſſembly of Generals. Yet they never took upon them to preſcribe to, or direct, the Perſons they employed; but left them to their full liberty, to act according to their own Judgment and Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Author</hi> cannot promiſe a Continuation of the <hi>Work</hi> here begun. He hath made ſome farther Remarks upon things that have happen'd in the progreſs of this VVar. and he hath imprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in his Mind. But it is uncertain, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will have the leiſure to digeſt them, and to make them fit for publick View. If he do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Baden</hi> (for any thing yet appears) will be the prime Favourite of thoſe Obſervations.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50124:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50124:5"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS UPON THE War of Hungary.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>TECKELY.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>WHile his <hi>Imperial</hi> Majeſty is engaged in a War with <hi>France,</hi> by the Inſtigation of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> (as it is conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed), who therein ſerved the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, great Severities are uſed againſt his Proteſtant Subjects of <hi>Hungary.</hi> who till then, and for a long time, had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the liberty of their Religion, eſtabliſh'd by Law. but both their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and likewiſe their Civil Liberties, (as themſelves complain) were now invaded and ſubverted. After extreme Sufferings, and to avoid a total Deſtruction, the <hi>Hungarians</hi> take Arms, Count <hi>Teckely</hi> being their Head: and maintain a War with various Fortune. The <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> concludes a Peace with the <hi>French</hi> King: and his Forces (now grown ſtronger in <hi>Hungary</hi>) having ſome Succeſſes, impale their Priſoners. The others in Revenge impale theirs. and both ſides grow weary of Impaling. But the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> being preſs'd very hard, fly to the <hi>Turk</hi> for Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour. The <hi>Grand Signior</hi> takes them into his Protection: and in their Quarrel, ſends a mighty Army againſt the Emperour, under his Grand Viſier <hi>Kara Muſtapha.</hi> Which the Emperour oppoſes with all the Force he can make, commanded by the High-born Prince, <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>Obſervations.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I ſhall not here meddle with the Juſtice of the <hi>Emperour</hi>'s or the <hi>Hungarians</hi> Cauſe. Since is depends much upon the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Kingdom, which I do not pretend to know. That may be juſt and lawful in <hi>Hungary</hi> or <hi>Poland,</hi> which would be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50124:6"/>in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>France.</hi> But ſurely it is much doubted, whether his Imperial Majeſty did well in point of Prudence, to ſuffer his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to be thus provoked, in ſuch Circumſtances of Time and Place. It was in a Time, when he had an Enemy upon his Arm, that was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſwallow up all <hi>Europe:</hi> and it was in a Place bordering upon the <hi>Turks,</hi> who are both willing to take, and able to uſe ſuch Advantages.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the <hi>French</hi> did ſecretly incite the Emperour to Severities, and his Subjects to Reſiſtance, it is no great wonder. For they had then a dangerous War with Him and his Confederates: and it is thought no Crime to uſe all ways and means, to weaken and diſtract an Enemy. But the wonder is, that the Jeſuits would be the Inſtruments of ſo great Miſchief to his Imperial Majeſty, who had ſo great a Favour for their Order. However this may ſeem leſs ſtrange, if we conſider that the Jeſuits are wiſe: and regard their Intereſt, more than their Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Obligations. They know that in great Affairs, Gratitude and good Nature look like fooliſh things. And therefore they might think fit to forſake, or even to betray, a Prince that loved them; thereby to gratify a Prince that was uſeful to them. The truth is, they wanted the Power of <hi>France,</hi> to defend and ſupport them againſt their great Enemy the Pope. who 'tis thought had much rather ſee the Jeſuits root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of Chriſtendom, than the Proteſtants out of <hi>Hungary.</hi> So that as things ſtood, we muſt not blame the Fathers, if they could deny no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the Impaling the Priſoners, and the Succeſs of it, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; that extraordinary Severities are not to be uſed to Priſoners of War, where the Enemy is in a Condition to retaliate. Upon the firſt Revolt of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> cauſed all thoſe that he took in fight, to be executed by the hands of the Hangman. But when he ſaw that the <hi>Dutch</hi> cauſed all whom they took, to be executed likewiſe without mercy; his dire Soul was forced to ſubmit to the neceſſity of fair War. as <hi>Grotius</hi> informs us, in his moſt excellent <hi>Belgick</hi> Hiſtory.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Count Teckeley</hi> is ſeverely cenſur'd for calling in the <hi>Turk</hi> to his Aſſiſtance. And ſurely if the Emperour's proceedings were juſt and good, and <hi>Teckeley</hi>'s Arms unlawful; his joyning with the <hi>Infidels</hi> was a great aggravation of his Crime. Nor doth the Neceſſity he was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to, in any meaſure excuſe him: ſince it was a Neceſſity of his own making. As he that hath robb'd a Man, may find a Neceſſity to kill him too, to prevent purſuit or diſcovery. Or as <hi>Catiline</hi> ſays in the Play;</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50124:6"/>
               <q>
                  <l>The Ills that I have done cannot be ſafe,</l>
                  <l>But by attempting greater.</l>
               </q>
               <p>On the other ſide, if the Imperial Miniſters did unjuſtly perſecute and oppreſs; the Neceſſity was then of their making, and the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it ly at their Doors. For where a Neceſſity brings Miſchief, the Authors of the Neceſſity are the Authors of the Miſchief. And to think it unlawful to joyn with Infidels againſt Chriſtians in any caſe whatſoever, is a very great Miſtake. For if Merchants be ſet upon by Chriſtian Pirates, and a Squadron of <hi>Algerines</hi> come by; who can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Merchants, if they joyn with thoſe worſt of Infidels to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve themſelves, and to deſtroy the Chriſtians that would deſtroy them? Upon which account the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> at our firſt trading into the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> did ſeveral times joyn with <hi>Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> againſt the <hi>Portugals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> are now enter'd the Liſts. And ſurely it is a noble Sight, when two great Champions are engaged againſt each other. They draw the Eyes of the whole World upon them, and are the Subject of all Mens Diſcourſes. Many ſuch Pairs have their Names recorded in the Books of Fame. But thoſe are moſt remarkable, who have had a Tug of ſome Continuance: whereby they might ſhew their Play, and give the utmoſt Efforts of their Skill and Courage. Such were <hi>Hannibal</hi> and <hi>Marcellus,</hi> the two elder <hi>Scipio</hi>'s and the two <hi>Haſdrubals, Michridates</hi> and <hi>Lucullus, Pompey</hi> and <hi>Serto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Vercingetorix, Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey.</hi> And after them, <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus</hi> and <hi>Arminius, Cerealis</hi> and <hi>Civilis, Trajan</hi> and <hi>Decebalus. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemain</hi> and <hi>Wittikind,</hi> who fought twelve Battels, may juſtly claim a room among theſe famous Combatants. So may <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt and <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth: who had almoſt continual Wars, and were brave Captains as well as mighty Princes. To whom may be added, the Great <hi>Gonſalvo</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Lautrec,</hi> ſtiff adverſaries in the Wars of <hi>Naples:</hi> and in the Wars of <hi>Piemont, Dom Ferdinand Gonſaga</hi> and the Marſhal of <hi>Briſſac.</hi> Then follow, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth and the Duke of <hi>Parma, Maurice</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and <hi>Spinola, Guſtavus Adolphus</hi> and Count <hi>Tilly,</hi> the ſame <hi>Guſtavus</hi> and <hi>Walſtein, Turenne</hi> and <hi>Montecuculi.</hi> Others I omit, and haſten back to the <hi>Hungarian</hi> War.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>VIENNA.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THE Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> being firſt in the Field, ſits down before <hi>Newhauſel:</hi> but upon the Enemies Advance he raiſes the Siege.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50124:7"/>And finding himſelf much over-power'd, he encamps near <hi>Raab:</hi> upon a River of that name, which there falls into the <hi>Danube.</hi> The Grand <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> comes on: and while his Main Body confronts the Duke, the <hi>Tartars</hi> tracing the River towards the head, ſoon find or make their way over. For which great blame is laid upon the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who had the Guard of the paſſages committed to them. But the Duke hereupon draws off to <hi>Raab</hi> Town, where he divides his Army. Himſelf and the Cavalry make their Retreat directly to <hi>Vienna:</hi> being ſhrewdly ruffled by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who fell upon them in their March unawares. The Foot are ordered to paſs the <hi>Danube,</hi> and to march to the ſame Place, there being Men firſt drawn out of them, to make up very ſtrong Garriſons for <hi>Raab, Comorra,</hi> and <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldſtat.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Duke's arrival at <hi>Vienna</hi> (from whence the Emperour and his whole Court were now retired) he marches over the Bridge into an Iſland of the <hi>Danube</hi> called St. <hi>Leopold,</hi> that lies over againſt the City. This Poſt he maintains a while: but afterwards deſerts it, for Reaſons not known, and marches clear away. Moreover his Foot arrive alſo in good time, and before the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> could come up with the Main of his Army. Who laid all things aſide, and overlook'd all Difficulties, to attacque this Imperial City. The Siege is carried on for two Months with all vigour and violence, and with very great loſs of Men. Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> commanded within the Place, and did well defend it. But however it was brought at laſt to great Extremities. Then come the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Forces, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> the Electors of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and Prince <hi>Waldeck:</hi> who rout the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, and relieve the City. And now Count <hi>Teckely</hi> deſires to ſubmit upon fair terms: but no terms would be given him. whereupon he renews his Alliance with the <hi>Turks.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> marcheth home with his Troops. The rest of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army advance into <hi>Hungary;</hi> and take <hi>Gran, Lewents,</hi> and other places. The Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> having rallied he remains of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Army, and ſtrangled ſeveral Baſſa's and other Officers for not doing their Duties; is afterward ſtrangled himſelf, to appeaſe the Rage of the Soldiers and People.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>Obſervations.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT muſt be confeſs'd, that in this beginning of the Campagne, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had a hard Game to play. as all have that muſt act upon the defenſive, againſt a much over-matching Enemy. But the Duke ſeems to have dangerouſly miſtaken his meaſures, in chooſing a Poſt which he was not able to maintain. which brought all things to the utmoſt hazard. How could he expect that the <hi>Tartars</hi> (of whom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50124:7"/>the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> had thirty thouſand) ſhould be ſtopt by a ſmall ſhort River; that make it their practice to ſwim over the <hi>Nieper,</hi> the <hi>Nieſter,</hi> and the <hi>Danube?</hi> Nor let the <hi>Hungarians</hi> be blamed for not defending the Paſſes, for it doth not appear how it was poſſible to be done. Had the Duke ſtrongly encamp'd under the Walls of <hi>Raab,</hi> and not at that diſtance he did, which was ſeven or eight Miles; as he had covered the Country in effect as well, ſo he had ſecured his Army much better. And perhaps he had done beſt, to have poſted himſelf yet more back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. What though ſome Frontier places had been thereby expoſed? It had been more adviſable to ſacrifice a part, than ſo greatly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the whole. And this ſeems to have been the Sentiment of the Marſhal of <hi>Crequi,</hi> when he managed a defenſive War againſt this Duke, in his own Country of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> He poſted himſelf at once up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Moſelle:</hi> leaving the <hi>Saar</hi> (as good a Stream as the <hi>Raab</hi>) and all the Places upon it, with the whole Country between thoſe two Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, open to the invading Army. Which he thought a leſs Evil, than to graſp what he could not hold; and thereby put his own Army (upon which the Fortune of <hi>France</hi> depended) in danger of a haſty and diſgraceful Retreat, or perhaps a total Ruine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the Duke's retreat to <hi>Vienna</hi> ſome People are unſatisfi'd with two things. The One is, that as his Troops were marching, the <hi>Tartars</hi> were upon them and among them, before they were in the leaſt aware of it. Which they think could not be, if the Duke had not ſtrangely want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Intelligence in the Emperour's own Country; and if he had taken care to ſend out his Scouts in due manner, and throughly to diſcover the ways by which he was to march, as cautious and skilful Generals uſe to do. The other thing is, that when theſe Troops were got to <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna,</hi> they never turn'd their faces toward the Enemy: but lay in that Iſland of St. <hi>Leopold,</hi> as it were without Life and Soul. I confeſs they might well be daunted with the diſgraces and dangers of their Retreat, and the diſmal condition of Affairs. But then they ſhould have been made to recover their Spirits by ſome ſucceſsful Encounters: of which there were fair Opportunities by the poſture the <hi>Turks</hi> were in. Who came up in ſcambling Parties, their main Body not arriving till ſeveral days after.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had now a hard Game, ſure the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> had an eaſy one. He commanded a mighty Force, which had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to withſtand or oppoſe it: the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army being broken up, and as it were quite vaniſh'd. So that he was now (if I may uſe an odd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50124:8"/>Expreſſion) like a Lord in a Hutch; he might turn himſelf which way he pleaſed. There was only one Caution to be uſed; That whereas the Chriſtians had mainly provided for the defence of four Towns, let what will become of the reſt; he would for the preſent forbear medling with thoſe Towns. but every where elſe he might go on conquering and to conquer: no other place being capable to make reſiſtance. A few Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of barbarous Cruelty toward thoſe that ſtood it out (to which the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s nature would eaſily have enclin'd him), and of good uſage to thoſe that readily yielded, would in that terror have open'd him the Gates of all thoſe Places. And in humane probability, he might that Summer have ſubdu'd all the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Dominions on the South ſide the <hi>Danube,</hi> the Towns of <hi>Raab</hi> and <hi>Vienna</hi> excepted. Or if he would be content with deſtroying the open Country, he might have done it ſo throughly in two or three Months time, as not to leave a Houſe ſtanding, nor hardly a Man or Beaſt living. And in the like ſpace of time he might have ſerv'd <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſo too, and other parts of <hi>Germany.</hi> It would have been ſuch a Deſtruction, as never was ſince the time of <hi>Attila.</hi> But the <hi>Viſier</hi>'s pride and folly and evil Genius, made him leave theſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and theſe certainties; to fall upon a ſtrong and populous City, that had a Army in Garriſon, that was a hundred Miles within the Enemies Country, and upon a great River which he was not ſure nor likely to command on both ſides. Nothing could break his Army, nor deliver thoſe Countries out of his hands, but ſuch a Siege</p>
               <p n="4">4. As it was a grand Error in the <hi>Viſier</hi> to undertake this Siege, ſo he committed divers others in the Proſecution of it. In the firſt place he deſtroy'd all the Country near him with Sword and Fire: by which means great quantities of Proviſions were deſtroy'd, that ſhould have been preſerved for the ſuſtenance of his Army. for want of which, he was fain to ſupply himſelf by Convoys from <hi>Hungary.</hi> Alſo when the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> advanced to relieve <hi>Vienna,</hi> he cauſed his Men to leave the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their Camp, in which they were ſtrongly fortified, and to meet their Enemies in the open Field. When as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> could not ſtay by it: having no Proviſions, wherewith the <hi>Turks</hi> abounded. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over when his Army went out to fight, he went not out with them; but ſhamefully ſtay'd behind, and kept at a diſtance. And when they were routed, and fled, he fled with the foremoſt, as faſt as his Horſe could carry him. without any offer to rally, or any endeavour to make a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat. His ſtrangling ſome of the run away Baſſa's afterward, did no way purge his own baſeneſs. take them at the worſt, they did but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Example. He therefore ſeems to have well deſerved his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50124:8"/>End: going off the ſtage inglorious and with the Character of a proud and cruel Coward.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I believe moſt men conclude, that the Emperour did very pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, in retiring from <hi>Vienna</hi> upon the Enemies Advance: thereby ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing his own Sacred Perſon. And I confeſs the ſafety of the Prince is a matter of higheſt Importance. But yet ſometimes wiſe Princes do lay aſide the thoughts of ſecuring their own Perſons, when all lies at ſtake. for in ſuch caſes, the place of greateſt danger is the place where the Prince ſhould be. The Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> did abſolutely ruine his Affairs by ſecuring his Perſon: and by avoiding preſent danger, did fall into a total and final Deſtruction. If the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> had retir'd from <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen,</hi> when it was ſet upon by the <hi>Swede;</hi> he might have ſecur'd his Perſon, but he had loſt both his City and his Kingdoms. whereas by his Preſence, and perſonal Gallantry, he preſerved all. And ſurely it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deny'd, but that this withdrawing of the Emperour did much weaken <hi>Vienna:</hi> from whence above threeſcore thouſand People are ſaid to have retired or fled upon that occaſion. If it be ſaid, that moſt of theſe were an unwarlike Multitude, I will admit they were. But had the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſtaid, every Man (and almoſt every Woman) would have been a Soldier in the preſence of his Imperial Majeſty. Moreover it had then been eaſy to defend the Iſland of St. <hi>Leopold:</hi> whereby the paſſage over the <hi>Danube</hi> had been kept open, and a Communication with all the Countries behind it. Which had made the Emperours ſtay at <hi>Vienna</hi> to be much more ſafe, and likewiſe much more honourable; than if he had been laid up in a place, which the Enemy might have begirt on all ſides.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Some think that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> notwithſtanding the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of the Emperour, and of thoſe that went out with him and after him, might well enough have defended the Iſland of St. <hi>Leopold.</hi> This Iſland lies cloſe to <hi>Vienna:</hi> being made by the <hi>Danube,</hi> and about four <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles in length. There is a Bridge into it from the City: and from it you paſs on, over two other ſmall Iſlands and three other Bridges, to the moſt Northern bank of the River: the City ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the moſt Southern. In the Iſland firſt mention'd the Duke placed himſelf, as hath been related. But he departed thence when the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> came up with his whole Army; which was ſeven or eight days after. Concerning which departure I ſhall ſet down the words of <hi>John Peter</hi> a <hi>Valcaren,</hi> Judge Advocate of the Imperial Army: who hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us a particular account of this Siege. and I think it is the beſt we have. <hi>The Duke of</hi> Lorrain, ſaith he, <hi>who hitherto remained with the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50124:9"/>Cavalry in the Iſland of</hi> St. Leopold, <hi>and as we thought did not intend to ſtir from thence, altering his reſolution, marched over the Bridges that lead towards</hi> Moravia <hi>with theſe Regiments,</hi> &amp;c. And afterward he adds; <hi>As for thoſe that were beſieged, they wiſhed nothing more, than that the Duke would have ſtaid in the Iſland of</hi> St. Leopold: <hi>which would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a free Communication and Entercourſe, as well with the Emperour, as with the territories of</hi> Bohemia, Moravia, Sileſia, <hi>and other parts of the Empire, from whence we might have receiv'd Supplies of every thing we needed. This was the opinion of the beſieged, who afterward felt thoſe hard. ſhips, that were brought upon them by the quitting of that place. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are not to doubt of the ſufficiency of the Reaſons, that moved the Duke of</hi> Lorrain <hi>to haſten his departure thence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Author knew thoſe ſufficient Reaſons, he did not well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal them. for it highly concern'd the Duke's honour, that Satisfaction ſhould be given to all men in this matter: whereas now, many remain unſatisfied. For the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had his whole Cavalry with him, which could not be leſs then eight or nine thouſand. And there was come to him the Prince <hi>Lubomirski</hi> with 4000 <hi>Poliſh</hi> Horſe, and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Schultz</hi> with 3000 <hi>Germans.</hi> He had alſo a great River between him and the Enemy. for though the <hi>Danube</hi> do there divide it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to four Branches, yet every Branch is a large and deep Stream. And of this he had but four <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles to guard: two above the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and two below it. Then as to Forrage, 'tis hard to believe but that all the one ſide of the <hi>Danube</hi> might maintain fifteen or ſixteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe, as well as fifty or ſixty thouſand were maintain'd by the other.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Though the Iſlands of the <hi>Danube</hi> were thus unhappily quitted, yet ſtill (the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> commanding the River, as having all the Veſſels both above and below the City); the beſt and eaſieſt way to relieve it, ſeems to have been by thoſe Iſlands. Had <hi>Maurice</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> been now alive, and directed theſe Affairs, (who as he had all the Arts of War, ſo particularly he ſeem'd in his Element when he was amongſt great Waters; and both exquiſitely knew, and could moſt dexterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe, all the advantages of commanding them): he would very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probably have gone this way, and have done his buſineſs without much hazard. The <hi>Turks</hi> had no Camp on this ſide, ſo fortifi'd as that on the other ſide was. Nor would their vaſt numbers (particularly of Horſe) have ſtood them in much ſtead amongſt theſe ſmall Iſlands. And though they might poſſibly have defended theſe their Quarters, yet ſo great a Force muſt be upon this Duty, that the Siege muſt in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50124:9"/>mean time have ſtood ſtill, or at leaſt could not be carried on with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Vigour. Moreover the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> might have attempted a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief this way, much ſooner than the other. for which they were ſo long preparing, that the City was in great danger to be loſt in the mean time. But the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army went the plain way to work: that is, they croſs'd the River, and marched in fair Order along the Southern bank of it, openly and directly upon the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Camp. And their glorious Succeſs ſeems to have juſtified their Counſels. But yet we muſt bear in mind; that they had certainly miſcarried, if their Enemies had not been quite mad; and by a prodigious Error quitted the advantage of their Ground.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army had ſuch Illuſtrious Commanders, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Princes were there engaged in perſon, that few Armies in the World can ſhew the like. The King and the two <hi>Electors</hi> commanded their own Forces, <hi>Lorrain</hi> commanded the Forces of the Emperour, and <hi>Waldeck</hi> the Forces of the Empire. And they all did their work ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and bravely. It muſt likewiſe be granted, that the <hi>Turks</hi> on their part left nothing undone for the gaining of their prize; and that they ſtrain'd themſelves to the utmoſt, to take the City before the Relief came up. continuing alſo to preſs very hard upon it, even while their Army was routing, and their Camp forcing. Nevertheleſs if their whole Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Affair be well conſider'd, we may obſerve in them more Induſtry and Pertinacy, than either Skill or Valour.</p>
               <p n="9">9. By the raiſing of <hi>Vienna</hi>'s Siege, and the deſtruction of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Army, the Scene of Affairs was quite alter'd. and the Emperour's Condition was now as high, as it had been low before. He could now think of nothing leſs, than of beating the <hi>Turk</hi> out of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward out of <hi>Europe.</hi> which later is the eaſier of the two. To accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh which glorious and dazling Enterpriſe, it much concern'd him to make up with his own revolted Subjects, upon any reaſonable terms. Which the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and likewiſe the Pope himſelf (as it is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently affirm'd) did adviſe and exhort him to. The Pope (whom all his actions declare to be a wiſe man) might well conſider, That the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eaſe to a few underling Proteſtants for a time, was an Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of no value: when it would bring with it ſuch vaſt advantages ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, and ſo great an enlargement both of the Emperour's Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and his own Eccleſiaſtical Dominion. Moreover the <hi>Hungarians</hi> were now very inclinable and deſirous to make their peace. in order whereunto, they made humble and repeated Aplications to his Imperial
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50124:10"/>Majeſty. But no Treaty with them would be hearken'd to: and they were given to underſtand, that they muſt ſubmit without Conditions. 'Tis true, they had afterwards a Pardon granted them: with a promiſe to preſerve their Civil and Religious Liberties. But the Terror of <hi>Vienna</hi> was then over: and they had renewed and ſtrengthened their Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy with the <hi>Turks:</hi> and they were then more hardened againſt the Emperour. So that Count <hi>Teckely</hi> and moſt of the chief Men, and all the ſtrong Places, ſtill refus'd to come in.</p>
               <p>The want of a Peace on this ſide was an infinite prejudice to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's Affairs. For the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who might have greatly increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Force, did now much divide and diſtract it. The King of <hi>Poland</hi> was not able to make good his Quarters in Upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> where the Revolters had ſo many Garriſons. And the <hi>Germans,</hi> who ſtaid it out, were put upon hard Duty. Alſo the ſame diſadvantage continued in the two following Campagnes: a great Force being employ'd all along a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Hungarians.</hi> They are at laſt in a manner totally reduced. But this Work might have been much more difficult, if <hi>Teckely</hi>'s Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment had not made it eaſy. And now the Caſtle of <hi>Mongatz,</hi> which is the only place remaining, doth ſtill make a conſiderable diverſion, and occaſions no ſmall hardſhips. Another ill Effect was, that ſoon after the Emperour's return to <hi>Vienna,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> went away home with his Troops, being ten thouſand good Men. Which it is believed he did, becauſe the Reſolutions againſt the <hi>Hungarians</hi> were ſo ſevere and inflexible, and becauſe his Interceſſion for them was rejected.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> hath made himſelf famous to the Worlds end by his gallant defence of <hi>Vienna.</hi> and he is worthily honour'd for it. But he ſuffers a little diminution, in the opinion of ſome Men, by a Letter he wrote to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> during the Siege. which was alſo print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made publick. Herein they are ſcandalized at it, becauſe it is ſo abominably Complemental. And truly I could wiſh, that this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had not been written. Flattering and fawning doth no way become a Man of Honour; and it alſo blemiſhes thoſe to whom it is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as if they delighted in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DA.</hi> 1684.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THE Grand <hi>Signior</hi> makes <hi>Kara Ibrahim</hi> Baſſa, his Chief <hi>Viſier;</hi> and <hi>Cheitan Ibrahim</hi> Baſſa, his Seraſquier or General for the War of <hi>Hungary.</hi> They get together a ſorry Army; moſt of them being new Men,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50124:10"/>and as much without Courage as Diſcipline. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> takes the Field about the ſame time. His firſt Action is the taking of <hi>Vicegrad:</hi> which is a Caſtle upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> between <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Buda.</hi> Then he march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es back to <hi>Gran;</hi> and paſſing the <hi>Danube,</hi> he advances toward the Enemy on that ſide. Part of the <hi>Turks</hi> Army engage the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> and are bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Whereupon the Duke poſſeſſes himſelf of <hi>Vacia,</hi> abandon'd by the <hi>Turks;</hi> and he batters and takes <hi>Peſt,</hi> which lies over againſt <hi>Buda.</hi> Then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes the <hi>Danube</hi> upon a Bridge of Boats. The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> retires, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Buda</hi> fifteen thouſand Men: which place the Duke beſieges. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incommoded by the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who lay at ſome diſtance; he marches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him with his Horſe and Dragoons, (which were about twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand), beats him, and routs his whole Army. Then he returns to the Siege, and falls cloſe to battering and ſtorming. By which, and by the Sallies of that rampant Garriſon, he ſoon loſt the greateſt part of his Infantry. So that now the Siege was at a ſtand. In the mean while a Peace is concluded in <hi>Flanders:</hi> chiefly by the Mediation and Labour of the States of <hi>Holland.</hi> By which means the <hi>Germans</hi> (whom the <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Affairs did much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, and who therefore kept a good Force upon the <hi>Rhine</hi>) were ſet free to march into <hi>Hungary.</hi> This they immediatey do: and particularly the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> with a good Army of his own. After theſe great Reinforcements, the Attacques at <hi>Buda</hi> are puſh'd on with all vigour. and on the other ſide the <hi>Turks</hi> makes an obſtinate defence. The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> mean while rallies and increaſes his Army. But not truſting to them, he keeps at a diſtance. However he hinders the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> all he can, from having Forage and Proviſions. By the want of which, and by the approaching Winter, and by other hardſhips and difficulties, they are enforced at laſt to raiſe the Siege. They draw off without diſturbance: their Army being in very ill condition. and being got over the <hi>Danube;</hi> they abandon <hi>Peſt,</hi> leave a ſmall Garriſon in <hi>Vacia,</hi> and retire to their Winter Quarters. Nor was it long, before <hi>Vacia</hi> was taken by a party of <hi>Turks</hi> out of <hi>Buda.</hi> During theſe Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, General <hi>Schultz</hi> (in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper <hi>Hungary</hi>) takes Count <hi>Teckely</hi> to task, who holds him hard to it. At laſt <hi>Teckely</hi> is ſurprized: and loſes his Baggage, with a good part of his Army. But yet afterward he makes good his Garriſons, and ſtands his ground.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>Obſervations.</head>
               <p n="1">1. UPon the firſt Defeat of the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> and the taking of <hi>Peſt</hi> and <hi>Vacia,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was in the ſame high Condition, that the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> was the year before. For there was now no Army that durſt look him in the face. And the <hi>Turks</hi> were ſhut out of Upper
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50124:11"/>
                  <hi>Hungary;</hi> having loſt their only Paſs upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> by loſing <hi>Peſt.</hi> Alſo the Duke's advantage was yet greater, when he had been ſuffer'd to lay his Bridge over the River. for now he might act on which ſide he pleaſed. He might March after the <hi>Seraſquier:</hi> and either drive him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> (and ſo out of the Country) without fighting; or certainly beat him, if he had fought. They that were ſo eaſily rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Cavalry, would have ſtood much leſs againſt his whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Then for the Garriſons; if he could but let <hi>Buda</hi> alone, there was ſcarce any other that was like to make any conſiderable reſiſtance. And Count <hi>Leſly</hi> being then in thoſe Parts, with a good Army, and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; the Duke and he joyning, muſt have born down all before them. Alſo if the Duke had kept on the other ſide of the <hi>Danube,</hi> he had found things there as eaſy. only <hi>Newhauſel</hi> was to be avoided at preſent: there being then in it an intractable Garriſon of ten thouſand Men. And perhaps <hi>Agria</hi> and <hi>Waradine</hi> might have held out a week or two. But for the other Places, they had been nothing in his hands. The eaſy taking of <hi>Zolnock</hi> and <hi>Saravas</hi> afterward (which are two of the beſt of them), doth plainly make it appear, how weak a defence they were like to make. So that in all probability, he might in a few Months have beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the <hi>Turks</hi> out of Upper <hi>Hungary.</hi> And then <hi>Teckely</hi>'s party muſt have fallen in likewiſe: together with the Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania.</hi> In this way the War would in a great meaſure have maintain'd it ſelf: and not have exhauſted the Emperour, in that grievous manner that the Siege of <hi>Buda</hi> did. The Duke's numbers would alſo have increaſed, by the coming in of the <hi>Chriſtian Hungarians,</hi> and Men flocking from all parts to the conquering Army. And all would have been in a flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition.</p>
               <p>Theſe things might have come to paſs, if the Duke had been pleaſed, (after the old Rule), to ſtrike the Nail where it would drive: and had taken care, not to put any thing to hazard, when he had ſo much ſure play. But nothing would content him but the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> which was too heavy for him. As if a man ſhould be amongſt Ingots of Gold; moſt of them portable, and ſome few not. and he ſhould chooſe, rather to break his back at once, with one that he could not carry; than take away the leſſer, at eaſe, one after another. after which, the greater, with a little patience, might be broken or melted down. One would think the freſh Example of the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s Fool-hardineſs, and the fatal Conſequences of it, ſhould have kept the Duke from committing the like Error. And 'tis a wonder how he could expect, that eighteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Foot (for his Army was reckon'd at thirty thouſand, and twelve thouſand of them were Horſe and Dragoons) could force a City, though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50124:11"/>not very well fortified, that had fifteen thouſand in Garriſon. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd that the Duke had very good Men. But then it was great pity that they ſhould be ſo uſed; ſo miſerably thrown away. Had they been put upon reaſonable ſervices, they might in all likelihood have crown'd themſelves with Victory and Honour, and their General with Glory.</p>
               <p>The beſt Army upon Earth may be baffled by an ordinary Enemy, if it attacque him in his ſtrength. which therefore good Generals avoid. <hi>Cambray</hi> was the Frontier againſt the <hi>French,</hi> and ſtood in their very teeth, the beſt part of two hundred years. But withal it was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrong, and always very well mann'd and furniſh'd. and therefore in all that ſpace they never attempted it, till now lately the time they took it. When the ſame <hi>French</hi> marched againſt <hi>Holland, Maſtricht</hi> lay juſt in their way. and they had threaten'd it hard. But ſince it had got a Garriſon of ten or twelve thouſand Men; they fairly paſt it by, as if there had been no ſuch Town. Afterwards, when the Garriſon was leſs by half, they fell cloſe to it; and had it upon reaſonable terms. But if they had fallen upon it at firſt, it might have broke their whole Army.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Rhetoricians</hi> tell us, that in <hi>Statu deliberativo</hi> there are two principal Queſtions; <hi>an utile? an poſſibile?</hi> and to both theſe, there muſt be good anſwers given, to make a Deſign adviſable. For 'tis idle to engage upon things that are eaſy, unleſs they be profitable withal; nor ſhould any proſpect of advantage tempt us to an Undertaking, if the thing be not poſſible, or (as the <hi>French</hi> and We better expreſs it) not feaſible. 'Tis confeſs'd that <hi>Buda</hi> was very convenient for the Duke. But muſt he therefore take it, whether he can or no? Muſt he therefore throw away his Army upon it, to no purpoſe? If a Stone Wall ſtand in a Mans way, muſt the Man run his head againſt it? The Advice which <hi>Quintilian</hi> gives his Orator, may be applied full well to a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; <hi>Conſulat vires ſuas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do again confeſs, that <hi>Buda</hi> is a place of great importance for carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the War. But is there no other Place worth the looking after? Surely there are many ſuch upon this Frontier; beſide thoſe farther in. There is upon the North ſide the <hi>Danube, Waradine,</hi> and <hi>Zolnock,</hi> and <hi>Agria,</hi> and <hi>Newhauſel:</hi> and upon the South ſide, there is <hi>Alba Regalis, Caniza,</hi> and <hi>Gradiſca.</hi> I will allow that <hi>Buda</hi> with <hi>Peſt</hi> is more worth than any two of them. But the worſt two of them is more worth than <hi>Buda</hi> without <hi>Peſt:</hi> which is the preſent caſe, the Duke having <hi>Peſt</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. We can therefore only conclude, that the gaining this City is to be mainly intended and endeavour'd, in a reaſonable way, and when ever there is power and opportunity.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50124:12"/>
               <p>That which is extraordinary in <hi>Buda</hi> is, its ſituation upon the <hi>Danube:</hi> and that the taking it opens this River to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> giving them free paſſage farther down for their Proviſions and other Neceſſaries. <hi>Gradiſca</hi> would do the ſame upon the <hi>Save,</hi> and <hi>Zolnock</hi> upon the <hi>Teys.</hi> but the Navigation of the <hi>Danube</hi> is much more conſiderable than either of theſe; it being the grand River, and coming from the chief Parts of the Emperour's Dominions. But I muſt take notice; That ſince the <hi>Christians</hi> had <hi>Peſt</hi> already on the oppoſite bank, it ſeems hardly poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hinder their paſſage up and down, in ſo great a Stream, near their own ſide, under the favour of dark Nights. Which makes the advantage of the Water, to be much leſs to this Town of <hi>Buda</hi> than was imagin'd. Then as for commanding the Land, the Towns before named do far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell <hi>Buda,</hi> as it is now without <hi>Peſt.</hi> for it now commands but one ſide of the River. And ſurely it is plain to any that will conſider; that a Town which ſtands upon a great River, not having a paſſage over it, is half block'd up. But the Towns before named command the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries clear round. eſpecially <hi>Agria, Newhauſel,</hi> and <hi>Caniza:</hi> which three are the fartheſt advanc'd, and which are the three Horns that gore the Imperial Territories. And <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> and <hi>Waradine</hi> do alſe command far and wide.</p>
               <p>But it may be ſaid farther of <hi>Buda,</hi> that here is the loweſt Bridge and Paſs upon the <hi>Danube:</hi> nor is there any other in <hi>Hungary, Gran</hi> only excepted. Which place and <hi>Barkan</hi> do yoke this River about forty miles higher, in the ſame manner as <hi>Peſt</hi> and <hi>Buda</hi> do here. In the old Maps of theſe Countries, there is the Mark and Picture of a Bridge at <hi>Colocza,</hi> forty miles lower. but there is no ſuch Bridge now to be found. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears then, that <hi>Gran</hi> was of the ſame Conſideration laſt year, that <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> is now. But the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> (if I may look back on what I have before omitted) did not do his part in defending it. He had got an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my together after his defeat at <hi>Vienna,</hi> by rallying and recruiting: the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> giving him leiſure to do it. for they made no great haſte to purſue their Victory. Part of his Army he loſt fooliſhly, by fighting the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in their March to no purpoſe. who thereupon poſſeſs'd themſelves of <hi>Barkan,</hi> on which ſide the Fight was. Then he let them paſs the River to attacque <hi>Gran,</hi> without Oppoſition. And which was worſt of all, He did not put Men enow into the Town, when he might have put in what number he would. Had he fill'd <hi>Gran,</hi> as the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier</hi> fill'd <hi>Buda, Gran</hi> might have been as well preſerv'd. And indeed much better and eaſier, becauſe of the Winter then approching. But this is a Digreſſion in this place: I return to the Siege of <hi>Buda.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50124:12"/>
               <p n="2">2. It is taken for granted by moſt Men, that when the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> had with his Cavalry defeated the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> he could do no leſs than return to <hi>Buda,</hi> and puſh on the Siege. But ſome are of a contrary opinion. They think, that having try'd the Strength of that Place and Garriſon (which was ſtill the ſame, notwithſtanding the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat) he had now a fair Occaſion given him, to leave a Siege upon which he had raſhly engaged. that he might purſue his Victory in a more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual manner, and march with his whole Army after the ſlying Enemy. Which if he had done, in all probability he had broke them to pieces; they could never have made head againſt him. If they found it ſo hard to get an Army again together, though the Siege of <hi>Buda</hi> gave them ſo great reſpite and leiſure; how could they have done it, if they had been cloſely followed? But the Duke would have been ſtop'd by the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> to which place the Enemy was fled. I anſwer, that this Bridge was then in a weak Condition, being not well fortified at either End. And the farther End being attacqued by Count <hi>Leſley</hi> next year, we know how eaſily it was taken. Alſo this Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> is four or five <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles in length; partly over ſeveral Branches of the <hi>Drave,</hi> and partly over low Grounds. Admitting therefore that the Ends were not to be taken: yet the middle part could not be defended, nor the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> hindred from paſſing over to it, without great numbers of Foot. and the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> had ſcarce any Foot left: the two defeats, and the Manning of <hi>Buda,</hi> having taken away moſt of them.</p>
               <p>Moreover it did much ſacilitate the Enterprize of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> that Count <hi>Leſley</hi> was then in thoſe parts with a good Body of Men. where he had taken <hi>Virovitza,</hi> a ſtrong Town upon or near the <hi>Drave:</hi> between which Town and the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> there was no Place of Strength. And <hi>Leſley</hi> commanded both ſides the River: and had laid (or was about to lay) a Bridge of Boats over it, having plenty of Veſſels for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And theſe might have been ſent down the Stream to the Duke at <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> as likewiſe Proviſions and other Neceſſaries. It appears then plainly, that the Taking of this Bridge was much more ſeaſible than <hi>Buda.</hi> And by the taking of it, <hi>Buda</hi> muſt fall in ſhort time, and all that the <hi>Turks</hi> have in Lower <hi>Hungary;</hi> this being their only paſſage to it.</p>
               <p>But what if the Duke had found this Bridge very ſtrongly guarded, and the gaining it very difficult? I anſwer, That then he muſt have let it alone as well as <hi>Buda.</hi> There was other eaſy work good ſtore, ready to his hand. and the more ſtrongly this Place had been guarded, the more unguarded other Places muſt be. Alſo the whole Country had lain open to him. the Country on this ſide the <hi>Drave,</hi> and that between the <hi>Drave</hi> and the <hi>Save,</hi> and beyond the <hi>Save</hi> alſo. He might have gone
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50124:13"/>which way he pleaſed, there being in effect no Army to oppoſe him. For as for the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> and his fugitive Rabble, they would have ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified nothing. And all had been full of Terror and Confuſion.</p>
               <p>Thus the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was fairly invited by his Victory to raiſe his Siege. Which alſo he ſhould have done without any ſuch Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He could not but be quickly ſenſible, that he had taken wrong mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in attacquing this City. and to perſiſt in an Error, wiſe Men ſay is the greateſt Error. Therefore very famous Commanders, when they have found themſelves engaged in a bad buſineſs, have eſteem'd it their wiſeſt courſe to get clear of it without delay. I ſhall inſtance only in two. The great <hi>Hannibal</hi> of old, after he had taſted the ſtrength of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia,</hi> made no ſcruple to leave it. And of later times, the great <hi>Guſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus</hi> thought it no diſhonour to riſe from before <hi>Ingolſtat,</hi> when he found it too hot for him. Had the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> done ſo here, he had been glorious: and in all probability the <hi>Turk</hi> had been totally ruin'd. As the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the year before, was the thing that preſerv'd the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperour; ſo nothing could now preſerve the <hi>Ottoman,</hi> but the Siege of <hi>Buda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may ſeem by the pains I have taken in this matter, that the deſign upon <hi>Buda</hi> is as hard to beat down, as the Walls of it are. But the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty is not yet quite over: for there remains a grand Objection againſt all that hath been ſaid. They ſay, That for the Duke to have marched on into the Enemies Country, leaving <hi>Buda</hi> behind him with ſuch a Garriſon in it, might have been of fatal Conſequence. That <hi>Buda</hi> muſt firſt be taken, to open the way to other places. And therefore ſince the attacquing of <hi>Buda</hi> was neceſſary, it could not be imprudent.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer; Firſt, that where a Frontier carries a breadth of three or four hundred miles, (and ſuch is the Frontier between the <hi>Turk</hi> and the Emperour, it reaching from the northerly parts of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> to the Gulf of <hi>Venice</hi>); it were very ſtrange, if there ſhould be but one way for a maſtering Army to break in upon it; and that all ſhould be guarded by one Town, without the taking of which nothing elſe could be done. I have already named ſeven Capital Garriſons, beſide <hi>Buda,</hi> upon this Frontier. And there are divers leſſer Places beſides. Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly there is <hi>Novigrad</hi> and <hi>Hatwan:</hi> which, after that the Duke had got <hi>Peſt</hi> and <hi>Vacia,</hi> ſeem'd next in courſe; being not far off, and on the ſame ſide the River. But where there is ſuch Choice of Places to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is the uſe of skilful Generals to learn the condition of each place, and to fall upon thoſe that are worſt provided. for all Places cannot be provided alike. And ſurely had the Duke been minded to do the eaſieſt things firſt, he might always have been doing the eaſieſt things; or to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50124:13"/>ſpeak plainer, he might have found all things eaſy. whereas now by at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting the hardeſt thing firſt, he hath made all things hard. For the <hi>Turks</hi> do now, by the Example of <hi>Buda,</hi> defend their Places after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rate than they did before. But had the Duke fallen upon likely things; he would, in all probability, have found no greater reſiſtance any where, than he found at <hi>Gran:</hi> which we know was very little. There was therefore no neceſſity for the Duke to fall upon <hi>Buda:</hi> ſince the Country was wide enough, and he might go either to the right hand or the left, as far as he could reaſonably deſire. By going to the Right hand, he had gone ſtraight upon the <hi>Drave,</hi> which brings all ſorts of Supplies out of the Hereditary Countries. down which River he had met with no <hi>Turkiſh</hi> place worth naming, till he came to <hi>Eſſeck:</hi> of whoſe weakneſs I have ſpoken before, and of its great Importance withal. On the other ſide, by going to the left hand he had gone ſtraight upon the River <hi>Teys:</hi> which brings all neceſſaries out of the Emperour's Upper <hi>Hungary.</hi> And the Place which the <hi>Turks</hi> have higheſt upon this ſtream is <hi>Zolnock:</hi> which we know was very eaſily taken next year, with divers Places about it. all which Places, and many more, might have been taken as eaſily now. We ſee therefore, that which way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Duke had turn'd, he might have found it commodious. But</p>
               <p>Secondly, if the Matteraright,
Duke had turn'd no way, but had march'd ſtraight on by <hi>Buda,</hi> and left that Place behind him; plainly there had been no harm nor danger in it. We find the like is frequently done by others. Not to run upon new Inſtances, the <hi>French</hi> (as hath been noted) paſt by <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> and have often paſt by <hi>Cambray:</hi> and even in this War, the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> when he march'd to <hi>Vienna,</hi> left behind him <hi>Comorra,</hi> and <hi>Raab,</hi> and <hi>Altenburg,</hi> and <hi>Newſtat,</hi> beſide other places. <hi>Newſtat</hi> was near his Camp: and he might have taken it with eaſe. which yet he neglected to do, and no harm came of it. It muſt be granted, that where the invading Army is oppoſed by an Army almoſt as good, in that caſe it were very hazardous to engage too deep in the Enemies Country. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Enemy by the help and favour of his Garriſons, might diſtreſs them very much, and have great advantaces upon them. But if the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my be quite over match'd, and dare not abide within diſtance; (which was now the condition of the <hi>Turks</hi>); there is then no ſuch danger. And Garriſons without an Army to ſtand by them, cannot hurt much: nor hinder the Invaders from going or ſtaying where they pleaſe, nor from picking and chooſing what work they will do. But they muſt take heed of undertaking any long and difficult Siege: as the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> did laſt year. though he furmounted the Incommodities of it, by the great Force he had about him. But it may be preſumed, that for the moſt part
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50124:14"/>their work will be eaſy. in regard the Places that lie farther inward, cannot in likelihood be ſo well fortifi'd and furniſh'd, as the Frontier Places are.</p>
               <p>I confeſs the taking of the outmoſt Frontier Garriſons, is a healing Work. ſince thereby we clear, and ſet at peace, ſuch parts of our own Country, as thoſe Garriſons did before command and harraſs. But it muſt be acknowledg'd on the other ſide, that the Places farther inward do more annoy the Enemy, as lying within their Bowels. If it be ſaid, that theſe Places, though perhaps they may be eaſily got, yet are hard to be kept, and hard to be relieved; I anſwer, that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may keep and relieve ſuch Places, as well as the <hi>Turks</hi> do <hi>Newhauſel, Agria,</hi> and <hi>Caniza.</hi> which though it be done with ſome difficulty, yet this is abundantly recompenſed by the great Miſchief, which thoſe Towns do to the Emperour. For which reaſon the <hi>Turks</hi> do juſtly ſet a high va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon thoſe Towns. And ſurely I think it will not be denied, but that it were a very great Service, if the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> could get three or four Places, as far advanced as the Towns laſt named. and which might gall and gore the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Countries, as much as the Towns laſt named do the <hi>Auſtrian.</hi> They that are the ſtronger, (which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are now), need not be affraid to ſcatter the War: but ſhould rather deſire it. Since thereby they do more diſtract the Enemy, and put him upon a ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Guard, and make him yet more unable to keep the Field.</p>
               <p>Theſe Notions are eaſily conceived by any conſidering Perſon: they naturally flowing from the things themſelves. but I have found it a work of ſome difficulty, to digeſt and expreſs them, and make them plain. Though perhaps to thoſe that read, even this alſo may ſeem eaſy, now it is done. Moreover I am very ſenſible, that I have been unreaſonably prolix upon this Subject. But I could not work my Matter aright, with fewer words.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was a rare felicity to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and ſuch as befals few Generals; that when he had loſt (I may not ſay deſtroy'd) one Army, he could ſit ſtill till another was brought to him. It calls to mind the Centurion in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> whom the Soldiers call'd <hi>Cedo alteram.</hi> becauſe when he had broken one Cudgel upon them, he us'd to cry <hi>Cedo alteram,</hi> give me another. But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> if he had had an Enemy any thing near his Match, and if at this time the <hi>Turks</hi> had not been ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weak, could not have had this leiſure. Alſo he might have ſtay'd and call'd long enough for a new Army, if the Peace of <hi>Flanders</hi> (which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd juſt at this time) had not given the <hi>Germans</hi> liberty to march to him. And this Peace was obtain'd beyond all Expectation. It was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50124:14"/>miraculous, that the <hi>French</hi> ſhould let go ſo great an Advantage: They that envy their Greatneſs, hope they will never have the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. But to ſay the truth, the advantage was loſt the year before. Had the <hi>French</hi> then fallen upon the Towns with all their Force, inſtead of Quartering upon the Country, (which they might have done with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Juſtice, and as ſome conceive with leſs Inſolence); they might have carried <hi>Flanders</hi> that very year, or at leaſt put it out of condition to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. But now ſuch Alliances were form'd to preſerve it, and ſo many Mediators had concern'd themſelves, that perhaps it was not ſafe to diſpleaſe them. However it may be truly ſaid upon the whole matter, that the <hi>French</hi> did not purſue their Intereſt in this occaſion, ſo cloſely as they uſe to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Machiavell</hi> tells us of divers Men, that ſadly miſcarried in their Affairs by not being perfectly wicked. which he ſaith is frequently the ruin of great Deſigns. Some may apply this to the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters: and may think that they loſt their Advantage here mention'd, becauſe they had not the Heart nor the Face to proſecute it. It ſeeming a little too hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid, while the <hi>Turk</hi> was deſtroying and devouring on the one ſide, for Them to do the like on the other. But it muſt be conſider'd, that it was not altogether ſo ſcandalous to fall upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> as it had been to fall upon <hi>Germany</hi> it ſelf, which was engaged in the <hi>Turks</hi> War. Alſo the <hi>Turks,</hi> after their defeat at <hi>Vienna,</hi> were not in an invading condition. and it was much more tolerable to ſtop the Emperour's Conqueſts, than to promote the <hi>Turkiſh.</hi> But moreover, the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters are of a ſtronger temper, than to be hinder'd from doing thoſe things that are convenient, either by the checks of Conſcience, or by the rebukes of Shame.</p>
               <p>What was the true Cauſe therefore of this ſtrange ſlack Conduct at this time? If the thing be well examin'd, it will be found to proceed from the <hi>Jeſuits:</hi> who we know have a great Aſcendant over that Court. They had ſeveral times betray'd the Emperour; and now they thought fit, in requital, to betray the <hi>French</hi> King: and to ſacrifice his Intereſts to theirs. It was the Intereſt of their Order, that the Emperour ſhould make great Conqueſts. By whoſe Favour (he being their faſt Friend) they might well hope to have many new Colledges, and ſome new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, of <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> which plainly would be much to the advantage of the Society. And though this might bring ruine to their great Patron of <hi>France,</hi> on whom the Emperour would in all likelihood turn his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Forces, they did not value it. The thing they mind, is the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of their Order. And this ſeems the true Reaſon, why the <hi>French</hi> King did let ſlip this golden Opportunity, of making himſelf the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarch.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50124:15"/>
               <p n="4">4. Of all the Mediators that labour'd in this Peace of <hi>Flanders,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> did labour moſt: and indeed it did moſt concern them. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of their Commonwealth at this time was full of difficulty and danger. for thus it ſtood. By the loſs of <hi>Flanders</hi> they muſt be certainly ruin'd: the <hi>French</hi> were reſolved to have a Limb of it, that is, the Town of <hi>Luxenburg:</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were reſolved to loſe all, rather than part with any thing. But they took little Care, and made little Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their defence: and ſeemed to caſt that wholly upon the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> as making account, that the Preſervation of <hi>Flanders</hi> did concern <hi>Holland</hi> more than <hi>Spain.</hi> And now was the Emperour engaged againſt the <hi>Turk: Denmark, Brandenburg,</hi> and <hi>Collen</hi> were cloſely ally'd with <hi>France:</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> ſeemed cool, and willing to be quiet. This was the perplext Eſtate of Affairs abroad. And it was as bad with the <hi>Dutch</hi> at home, by reaſon of their inteſtine Diviſions. The City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and the Province of <hi>Frieſland,</hi> did utterly refuſe to engage in the War. and they gave ſuch Reaſons for it, as ſeem not eaſy to be anſwer'd. On the other ſide, the Heroick Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>States,</hi> were fully determin'd to hazard all, rather than the <hi>French</hi> ſhould get <hi>Flanders.</hi> Moreover theſe Diviſions, in a Matter ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and in ſo dangerous a Conjuncture, were carried on with all the Animoſity imaginable: and were ready to break out into open Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. So that upon the whole they were brought to very great Straits. their beſt Friends gave them for loſt: and their Republique ſeem'd to be come to its fatal period. It may ſafely be affirm'd, that their Affairs were in a worſe poſture when the <hi>French</hi> beſieged <hi>Luxenburg,</hi> then when (ſome years before) they were poſſeſs'd of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht.</hi> But out of this grievous Labyrinth they extricated themſelves to admiration. For by great Patience, Art, and Induſtry, they at laſt hammer'd out a Peace between the two Crowns; whereby the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were forced to ſit down with the loſs of <hi>Luxenburg,</hi> and were made incapable to loſe or part with any more. The <hi>French</hi> being obliged not to take it, either by Conqueſt, Exchange, Gift, Ceſſion, or by any other way or Pretence.</p>
               <p>This Treaty may, in point of Negotiation, be accounted the Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of that Republique. Wherein they ſhewed as much Skill and Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, as they did Conſtancy and Fortitude in the time of the <hi>French</hi> Invaſion. for which they will be admir'd in all After Ages. They then ſuſtained ſuch a Shock, ſuch a Ruffle, ſuch a terrible Storm, as never did any People ſuſtain and endure the like. The <hi>Romans</hi> put a high va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon themſelves, for that when <hi>Hannibal</hi> lay on the one ſide of their City, they ſent out at the other ſide Supplies for <hi>Spain.</hi> And I confeſs it was brave and great. But it may be conſider'd, That they then with great
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50124:15"/>Force held <hi>Capua</hi> beſieged, which <hi>Hannibal</hi> had in vain attempted to relieve: that in the main they had got the better end of the Staff: and that plainly their City was in no danger. How much more firm and ſteady were the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who though they had a mighty Enemy in their Bowels, that was quite too ſtrong for them; though moſt of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was over run and ſubdu'd, and to ſave the reſt they were fain to lay a good part of it under Water; though at the ſame time they had a dreadful Concuſſion within themſelves, having with Violence chang'd their Government, not only into other Hands, but into another Form; Yet in the midſt of theſe diſmal Circumſtances they carried on a War at Sea, as if nothing had ailed them, as if they had had nothing elſe to think on. Where they ſought three Battels this very year, againſt the conjoyned Forces of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> I muſt crave pardon if I could not paſs this by, though it be a little beſide my Subject.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Upon the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s defeat at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and afterward his death, two things had been proper for his Maſter the Great <hi>Sultan</hi> to do. The firſt was, to go to the <hi>Hungarian</hi> War in Perſon: the Occaſion being ſo important, and all his Fortunes lying now at ſtake. How could he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that others ſhould fight for him, if he would not fight for himſelf? And how could he truſt his Empire, and the very Being of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Race, in other mens hands and to the Conduct of others; and himſelf ly lurking amongſt his Concubines? His Preſence would have given Life and Vigour to his Affairs: and raiſed up the Spirits of his diſmai'd and drooping Subjects. Nor is there any Office ſo proper to a Prince, and wherein he appears ſo glorious, as to lead his People to Battel. The other thing was, that if he could not go himſelf, he would take care that he that did go (in Chief), ſhould be inveſted and irradiated with the higheſt Authority. Or to ſpeak plainer, That none leſs than the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> ſhould be General in that War. So that if the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> was not the very fitteſt to be General, he that was fitteſt to be General was to be made Grand <hi>Viſier.</hi> For this was not a time to advance Favourites, but to employ the beſt Men to moſt advantage. The want of the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's preſence would have been made up in good meaſure by the preſence of ſo great an Officer. His Army (on which all depended) would have been better ſupplied, being ſupplied by him that commanded it. And the General Himſelf would have been better followed and obeyed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the full Power of Rewards and Puniſhments. We know the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> in times of extreme danger, made Dictators with abſolute Power. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second had never ſtop'd the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Torrent (which then was very impetuous); if he had not given abſolute Power to <hi>Walſtein</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50124:16"/>his Generaliſſimo. It ſeems therefore a Miſtake in the Great Sultan here, that he committed this ſo important Service to an Underling General: not giving him Authority ſuitable to the occaſion. For he made one Man his Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> and another Man his <hi>Seraſquier.</hi> To the one he gave the Honour and Authority, and expected the Service from the other. He appointed one Man for Preparations (which ſort of People Sir <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rawleigh</hi> doth contemne), and another for Action: and this Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration-Man was to command the Man of Action.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It muſt be avow'd, that this <hi>Seraſquier</hi> did extraordinary things, conſidering the diſadvantages he lay under. He not only wanted Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority requiſite, that is, the whole command of the whole <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; but alſo he had in effect no Army. For the People he had about him did not deſerve that name. They were partly ſuch as had fled from the Rout at <hi>Vienna,</hi> where all the beſt Men had been cut off; and partly raw undiſciplin'd People. And all of them (together with that whole Empire) were under exceeding Diſcouragement and Conſternation. So that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had gain'd no great Honour, though he had to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally beaten a General ſo ill followed, being ſo well followed himſelf. But though the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> were in this low condition, yet he bore up for two Summers, and maintained his ground without conſiderable Loſs: when in all likelihood he muſt have loſt all. Which muſt be aſcribed to his own good Conduct, as well as to the Errors of his Enemies. That which he did this year, was the relieving of <hi>Buda:</hi> which was a ſignal Service. He durſt not come within danger of fighting with the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> for he could not truſt his Men: finding they would not ſtand, and having been already twice routed. But he chiefly effected his Deſign by lying at a diſtance from his Enemies, and cutting off their Forrage and Victuals. whereby he greatly diſtreſſed and diſabled them. <hi>Guſtavus Horn</hi> adviſed, that the like might be done at the Siege of <hi>Ratisbon:</hi> but his Counſel was not followed. And ſome think that the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> might have done the like at <hi>Vienna:</hi> and not ly at <hi>Lintz,</hi> a hundred miles off, as he did the moſt part of that Siege.</p>
               <p>Though the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s Conduct in the Main were excellent, yet in ſome particulars it is thought he did not do well. He ſhould not have been ſo forward (or ſo eaſily forced) to fight, when there was no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for it. And he ſhould not have ſuffer'd his Enemies to lay a Bridge and paſs over the <hi>Danube,</hi> in the face of his Army, without fighting. He ſeems alſo to have loſt <hi>Peſt</hi> too eaſily: while Himſelf and his whole Army were on the other ſide the River, with a free paſſage to it over the Bridge. Whereas he ſhould have engaged his whole Force, together with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50124:16"/>his own Perſon, in defence of that Place. For it was of very great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; <hi>Buda</hi> being without it but like a half-fac'd Groat, if I may ſo expreſs the Matter. And he could never expect to cope with his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at better advantage. Nor could he hope to recover the Place, when he had thus loſt it, ſo eaſily as he did ſoon after. There was another thing that did more offend his great Maſter, and for which he was in diſgrace for ſome time: and that was, his not falling upon the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> when they drew off from <hi>Buda.</hi> But others think, that he was not to be blamed, if, notwithſtanding the ill Condition of the Enemy, he could not yet truſt his Men: that he might well be content with the great Succeſs of raiſing the Siege, and had now no reaſon to hazard all by fighting. And ſurely it was much wonder'd that the <hi>Sultan</hi> ſhould frown upon his Preſerver: when it was rather expected, that the higheſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Honours ſhould be heaped upon him.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Since the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> could not obtain what he principally deſign'd, it concern'd him the more to keep what he had gotten: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Vicegrad, Peſt,</hi> and <hi>Vacia.</hi> Of theſe <hi>Peſt</hi> was the moſt conſiderable, in that it held <hi>Buda</hi> ſtill in fetters, and pinn'd it up to one ſide of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube.</hi> And the Men there in Garriſon might be ſupplied with all Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries down the Stream, with almoſt as much eaſe as Quarter'd in <hi>Auſtria.</hi> And the more Men were there, the farther would they command, and the more Forrage, Victuals, and Contribution would they get. We are therefore to learn the Reaſons, why this important Place was quitted; and that without Burning or Demoliſhing. When there could be no fear of a preſent Siege, the Winter being ſo far advanced; and when the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy could not eaſily come at them, by reaſon of the River between. <hi>Peſt</hi> being thus abandon'd, one would think they ſhould have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er care of <hi>Vacia:</hi> which is alſo a Port Town (as I may call it) upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> and now the fartheſt advanced into the Enemies Country. But ſuch a paltry Garriſon is left in it, that after a few Weeks were paſt, a Party from <hi>Buda</hi> ſeizes it, almoſt without reſiſtance. Theſe After-Claps, though they made no great noiſe, doubled the diſaſters of the <hi>Campagne.</hi> For <hi>Vacia</hi> and <hi>Peſt</hi> may be accounted of equal value with <hi>Buda:</hi> and the loſing of theſe was as bad, as the not gaining the other.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The <hi>Hungarians</hi> of <hi>Teckely</hi>'s party that have been in <hi>England,</hi> have given him a very high Character. Extolling his Courteſy, Courage, and Conduct, and likewiſe the Comelineſs of his Perſon. It muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd, that by the great Reſiſtance he hath made, and the great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity he hath maintain'd amongſt his Party in a Condition ſo ruinous,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50124:17"/>he appears to be no ordinary Man. But he loſt his Honour by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to be ſhamefully ſurpriz'd: whereby his Forces were ſhrewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhatter'd, himſelf hardly eſcaping. The beſt Commander may receive a Defeat: but to ſuffer a Surprize is inexcuſable. On the other ſide, this Count ſhewed a notable Reſolution, in that after ſuch a terrible Blow he ſtill ſtood firm; and undauntedly continued his defence, againſt an Active and vigorous Aſſailant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>NEWHA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SEL.</hi> 1685.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> begins the Campagne once more with the Siege of <hi>Newhauſel:</hi> having a brave Army of between fifty and ſixty thouſand good Men, and the Garriſon within being now but two thouſand. The Place is fiercely defended: and in one of their Sallies, the Duke is put to the Exerciſe of his Perſonal Valour, to ſave his Batteries from ruine. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in a Months time or thereabouts, the beſieged are brought into an ill Condition. In the mean while the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> with an Army not much outnumbring that of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> had inveſted <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Vicegrad.</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve which Places, the Duke (with the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi>) marches with about two Thirds of the Army: leaving the reſt, under the Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> to continue his Siege. The <hi>Turks,</hi> having taken <hi>Vicegrad</hi> in three days, riſe from before <hi>Gran,</hi> fight the Duke with their whole Force, and are bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. However, they make their retreat to <hi>Buda,</hi> paſs over the Bridge there, and threaten to march ſtraight to <hi>Newhauſel</hi> and relieve it, with the hazard of a ſecond Battel. But now they hear that the Place was taken by Storm: where all were put to the Sword, ſave the Governor and a few Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. Nevertheleſs, the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> ſtill gives out, that he is reſolved to fight. But when the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with their whole Army were coming up to him, he repaſſes the <hi>Danube</hi> at the ſame Bridge, having firſt demoliſh'd and abandon'd <hi>Vacia</hi> and <hi>Novigrad.</hi> Being got to the other ſide of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, he continues there with his Army for ſome Weeks: and then, for want of Forrage and Victuals, retires to <hi>Belgrade.</hi> While he ſtaid, he ſent ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meſſages to the Duke with Overtures of Peace: which were rejected. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s repaſſing the <hi>Danube,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to the place where the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army had lain, and there Encamped for about a Month. And Forage growing ſcarce, he draws back his Army, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camps for another Mouth between the Rivers of <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Ipol:</hi> having firſt ſent the Count <hi>Caprara</hi> with a Detachment towards <hi>Agria.</hi> While the <hi>Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Forces are drawn from all parts to the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> Count <hi>Leſley</hi> marches to the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> and having routed the Forces that made head againſt him, he takes the Town of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> (which lies at the Bridge end) by ſtorm:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50124:17"/>and burns it, with eight or nine hundred Paces of the Bridge. Which done, he returns to <hi>Virovitza.</hi> The Works of <hi>Newhauſel</hi> are repaired with all diligence, and neither labour nor coſt is ſpared: but <hi>Novigrad</hi> and <hi>Vacia</hi> are not thought worth the repairing. General <hi>Schultz</hi> doth again fall cloſe to <hi>Teckely,</hi> is ſoundly repuls'd at <hi>Unguar,</hi> and then takes <hi>Eſperies</hi> after a hard Siege. Whence he marches ſtraight to <hi>Caſchaw,</hi> Count <hi>Teckely</hi>'s chief Town. <hi>Caprara</hi> having bombarded <hi>Agria</hi> without Succeſs, marches to <hi>Caſchaw</hi> likewiſe: bringing with him an Authority over all the Forces there. Whereupon <hi>Scultz</hi> lays down his Command. General <hi>Mercy</hi> and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Heuſler,</hi> with a Party from hence, fall into the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Quarters: take <hi>Zolnock, Saravas,</hi> and ſeveral other Places; which they hold and make good againſt the Enemy, and are victorious in divers Encounters. The Siege of <hi>Caſchaw</hi> going on, <hi>Teckely</hi> goes to the Baſſa of <hi>Waradine</hi> to ſolicit for relief: by whom he is made Priſoner, and ſent in Chains to <hi>Belgrade.</hi> Hereupon the brave <hi>Peterhaſi,</hi> and all the Chief of <hi>Teckely</hi>'s party, come in to <hi>Caprara.</hi> by whoſe Example and Perſwaſions <hi>Caſchaw</hi> Surrenders, and all the other revolted Places, <hi>Mongatz</hi> only excepted. While theſe things are doing in <hi>Hungary,</hi> the <hi>Venetians</hi> are not idle on their ſide. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Victory at <hi>Vienna,</hi> they had joyn'd in a League againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> with the <hi>Emperour</hi> and King of <hi>Poland.</hi> And againſt the next Summer, they rigg'd out their Fleet, and fill'd it with Land Soldiers, <hi>Moroſini</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Captain General. who took the Iſland of St. <hi>Maure,</hi> together with the Fortreſs of <hi>Preveſa</hi> upon the Main Land of <hi>Greece.</hi> This Summer they go to Sea again, with greater Force: and make a Deſcent into <hi>Morea.</hi> where they take <hi>Corone, Calamata,</hi> and ſome other places. Alſo they rout the <hi>Turks</hi> more than once, and divers <hi>Chriſtian Greeks</hi> revolt to them. As for the <hi>Poles,</hi> both the laſt year and this, their Forces are not great, came late into the Field, and did little.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>Obſervations.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE Siege of <hi>Newhauſel</hi> was carried on very ſubſtantially by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> He firſt made a great ſemblance of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging <hi>Novigrad,</hi> ſo that no body doubted of it: And then he clapp'd down ſuddenly before <hi>Newhauſel.</hi> which though it be uſual amongſt the <hi>Dutch, French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and other wily Gameſters; yet in theſe Wars of <hi>Hungary</hi> it may paſs for a Stratagem. Alſo before he began his Attacques, he ſtrongly intrenched himſelf, and finiſhed his Lines of Circumvallation. at which he made his whole Army labour for a full Week. And this being done, he puſh'd on his Attacques with great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and Vigour. Moreover he ſignalized himſelf by his own Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50124:18"/>Valour, when the <hi>Turks</hi> (in a furious Sally) were juſt upon the point to burn his Platformes and ruin his Batteries. In which Exigence, the Duke himſelf did run into the face of danger; to encourage and direct his Men, and to beat back the Enemy. continuing ſeveral hours in this ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Service. This was a moſt Heroique Action. If <hi>Alexander,</hi> or <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> or <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus</hi> had been here, they could not have done more. Nor did he thus hazard his Perſon upon a ſmall or ſlight occaſion. For the Succeſs of the Siege, and conſequently of the whole Campagne, now lay at ſtake. Furthermore, when the Duke was called away to the relief of <hi>Gran, Caprara</hi> did well ſupply his place here. And he did not expoſe and throw away his Men by vain and multiplied Aſſaults; but having throughly batter'd the Place, fill'd the Ditches, and broke the Defences, he carried it at once. One thing hath been omitted, which is, that the Duke's Judgment muſt be approved, in chooſing to fall upon <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> rather than any place elſe. For it ſorely infeſted the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Quarters, and by taking it he cleared a Country as big as <hi>Kent.</hi> And though it was believed, that they were already diſtreſs'd for Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, ſo that there was no need of Force; yet it was good to make ſure of a Place ſo important. Nor was their want of Victuals ſo great as was imagin'd: as it appeared afterward.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the juſt Commendations of this memorable Siege. But on the other ſide, Some think that it was ſlow. The Town was but indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently mann'd; and fortified by one ſingle Line, and a Ditch about eighteen foot broad. And yet they were more than a Month about it. Whereas it is verily believed, that a <hi>French</hi> Army would have had it in a Week. They took <hi>Maſtricht</hi> in fifteen days, which was twice as ſtrong, had thrice as many Men, and was full as well defended; with an Army no way better, or to ſpeak more truly, not ſo good. Some al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wonder, that <hi>Caprara</hi> did ſpare the Governor Baſſa. which look'd as if he had had a mind, to encourage others to hold out with the like Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy. Had this Baſſa had <hi>Caprara</hi> thus in his power, he would have impaled him. To ſpeak more calmly, the Baſſa ſeem'd no fit Object of Mercy, upon two accounts. Firſt, becauſe he had been barbarouſly cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el to his <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Priſoners: whom he had made work in Chains in the Mouth of the Beſiegers Cannon, whereby moſt of them were deſtroy'd. Secondly, becauſe he had ſtood it out beyond all Reaſon and the Rules of War. Which allow not Men to do all the Miſchief they can, when there is no hope left, nor poſſibility of defence. In ſuch a Caſe, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ought to find leſs favour than others, and the Governor leaſt of all. for that He was chiefly (if not only) in fault. The <hi>Turks,</hi> and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally their Commanders, ſhould be made to fear their Enemies as much
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50124:18"/>as they do their Maſters. If they yield, they are ſure to dy: and they ſhould be as ſure on't, if they yield nor. which is the way to deal with thoſe People, that fight for fear of death. Some think that the Baſſa's Ranſom might incline Count <hi>Caprara</hi> to ſpare him. wherein I am conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent they do the Count Wrong. For we muſt not believe, that ſo brave an Officer ſhould omit a neceſſary and exemplary piece of Severity, out of a ſordid deſire of Gain. But this Baſſa dyed of his Wounds not long after: and then they cut off his Head, and ſet it upon a Pole. Which ſeem'd very idle and fooliſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us now conſider the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s Conduct: which ſurely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears very neat and clean. He had Orders from the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Newhauſel</hi> at any rate, and what ever the hazard were. And theſe Orders he muſt obey, whether they were wiſe or fooliſh. But he ſaw plainly, that to march to that place, and fight the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, had been certain deſtruction. they ſo much over-matching him in goodneſs of Men, and the place being ſo far within the Enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. He therefore, by way of diverſion beſieges <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Vicegrad,</hi> which ly on the other ſide the <hi>Danube.</hi> Upon which, one of theſe three things muſt follow. Either the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army muſt come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theſe Places, and then <hi>Newhauſel</hi> had been at liberty; or elſe they muſt all continue their Siege, and then both <hi>Vicegrad</hi> and <hi>Gran</hi> had been his own; or part of them muſt march againſt him, and part muſt ſtay at the Siege: and then thoſe that ſtaid, would carry on the Siege but weakly; and thoſe that march'd, would be in a fair way to be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. The <hi>Chriſtians</hi> took this laſt Courſe, and divided their Army. But they proved ſo ſtrong; that they that ſtaid, were enow to take the Town; and they that march'd, were enow to beat the <hi>Seraſquier.</hi> However it muſt be confeſs'd, that he plaid the utmoſt of his Game. I know it hath been related, that he was drawn by a Wile to fight. But plainly at that time fighting was his Buſineſs: for without it <hi>Newhauſel</hi> muſt be loſt, and all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army would then be upon him. It was therefore much better, to engage part of the Enemies Force, thereby to ſave the Town; then ſuſtain their whole Force, after the Town was loſt. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over he ſet upon that part of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> which he was to Encounter, with all the Force that he could poſſibly get together. And he brought them up bravely to the Charge, and tryed to the utmoſt what every part of them could do. But they were beaten every where: not being able to ſtand againſt the <hi>Germans,</hi> who plainly hewed them down. Being thus totally routed, he nevertheleſs got off ſtrangely without extraordinary loſs, and made his retreat to <hi>Buda.</hi> There he march'd over the Bridge,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50124:19"/>and put on a freſh countenance of fighting. Which made the Dukes of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> after ſome time, to come down upon him with the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army, throughly prepar'd for a ſecond Battel. And then the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> ſlipt back over the River, and left his Enemies at gaze. for truly he was not in a fighting Condition. The Bridge of <hi>Buda</hi> ſtood him now in good ſtead: and in it he reaped the fruit of his labours. for he had been repairing it all Winter with great diligence; it having been ruin'd, when the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> held <hi>Peſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It may truly be ſaid of the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> that he loſt <hi>Newhauſel</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly. becauſe, to preſerve it, he did all that could be done. But it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid, that the Duke did ſo by <hi>Vicegrad,</hi> for it was pitifully loſt. This Caſtle ſtood (for it is now demoliſh'd) upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> with a Town under it: almoſt the mid-way between <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Buda.</hi> And it was the fartheſt Frontier on that ſide. If the <hi>French</hi> had had this Place, how would they have fortified and furniſh'd it? And what a tearing Garriſon would they have had in it? The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> had time enough to do what they would to it, it being a year in their Poſſeſſion. But it was ſo miſerably unprovided, that firſt a Party out of <hi>Buda</hi> ſurprized (or ſeized) the Town, plunder'd it, and burnt it: for which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour was never queſtion'd. And now a Detachment from the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier</hi> took the Caſtle by Surrender in three days: in a manner within ſight of the Duke and his Army. Which I confeſs was a very ſenſible diſgrace. This place and <hi>Gran</hi> had been threaten'd for a Month before, and the Duke might have put into them what Men he pleaſed: they ſtanding on the one ſide the River, and he commanding the other. 'Tis true, he put five hundred Men into <hi>Gran</hi> (when he might and ſhould have put in five thouſand.); but <hi>Vicegrad</hi> ſeem'd quite forgotten. If he could not or would not defend it, why did he not ſlight it? To conclude this Matter, the loſs of <hi>Newhauſel</hi> was far the greater in point of profit, and advantage, and importance; but in point of honour, the loſs of <hi>Vicegrad</hi> was a hundred times worſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To the Meſſages of Peace, which were ſent by the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> the Duke return'd this Anſwer, That a Victorious Army was not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſed by ſuch Meſſages. But what doth he do with this Victorious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my? What Conqueſts, or even what Attempts doth he make? Why firſt he encamps upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> a little ſhort of <hi>Peſt.</hi> And that he might be ſure to want Forrage in good time, it was juſt in place where the <hi>Turks</hi> had lain before. Accordingly Forrage is wanting, and he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move. But now inſtead of advancing into the Enemies Country, which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50124:19"/>lay right before him and open to him, he Marches quite back into his own: and there makes another encamping between the Rivers of <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Ipol.</hi> Which two encampings having taken up two pretious Months, and the year being now well ſpent (though as yet no hard weather); he ſends his Army into their Winter Quarters. Was ever Victorious Army ſo employed? Was ever Victory ſo purſued? If <hi>Alexander,</hi> or <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtavus Adolphus</hi> had been here, they would have purſued it after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner. <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Victory at <hi>Alexia,</hi> was one of the greateſt that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was obtain'd by Man. He had driven a brave Army of fourſcore thouſand Men into that Place, and held them there beſieged: his own Army being much leſs. And two hundred and fifty thouſand bold Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers came to relieve them. They fell upon his Trenches, (for here was the pattern of all our Circumvallations) T they fell upon his Trenches on both ſides, with the moſt obſtinate Fury. But thoſe without, were not only repulſed, but totally routed, leaving fifty thouſand dead upon the place; and thoſe within were beaten back with great loſs, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſurrender at diſcretion. Of this glorious Victory <hi>Caeſar</hi> had loſt the fruit, if he had not cloſely followed his blow: keeping his Men up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſervice, for a good part of the next hard Winter.</p>
               <p>All the World condemns <hi>Hannibal,</hi> for that he did not march ſtraight to <hi>Rome,</hi> after the Battel of <hi>Cannae.</hi> And we find him in <hi>Livy</hi> curſing and banning himſelf for this fatal Omiſſion, when afterwards he left <hi>Italy</hi> (full ſore againſt his Will) to reſcue his own dear <hi>Carthage.</hi> But though <hi>Hannibal</hi> did not do that which was beſt, yet he did ſomething; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as here our Duke does juſt nothing. It was <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Error, that he did march to <hi>Capua,</hi> when he ſhould have marched to <hi>Rome:</hi> But Our Duke doth march neither one way nor other, takes no work in hand, but trifles away his Time in idle encampings.</p>
               <p>Our Illuſtrious Duke is juſtly reputed one of the Greateſt Captains of this or any Age. But we have found by former Experience, that he is a little too much given to encamping, when the Seaſon calls for Action. When he march'd with a mighty Imperial Army into his own <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> (under <hi>Crequi</hi>) were in a manner fled out of the Country; in this ſo inviting, ſo provoking an Occaſion, he for ſeveral Weeks lay encamped upon the Banks of <hi>Saar:</hi> when all <hi>Europe</hi> expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his progreſs with impatience. I confeſs this might have done well, if he had come only to take the Air: but conſidering the Buſineſs he was upon, 'tis hard to be underſtood. I meddle no further with that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Campagne; which went on as it began.</p>
               <p>To return therefore to <hi>Hungary;</hi> it ſeems very ſtrange (for I cannot yet leave this Matter) that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> having ſo great an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50124:20"/>did not bear in upon the Enemy with all his power: and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly upon the Country between the <hi>Danube,</hi> and the <hi>Tibiſque,</hi> or <hi>Teys.</hi> It is a very good Country, and was then freſh and untouch'd: no Army having lain upon it, or ſo much as march'd through it. And it was cloſe at hand: and lay as open to him, as <hi>Kent</hi> doth to <hi>Surrey.</hi> Alſo there was no Enemy to oppoſe him. For the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> and his heartleſs Rabble were on the other ſide the River, not daring to look towards him; and after a while were gone clean away. ſo that now there was no Army in <hi>Hungary</hi> beſide the Duke's. Theſe Invitations notwithſtanding, he could not diſpoſe his mind to move that way; though he had nothing elſe to do. As if he had been Enchanted; or ſome Spell had been laid before him, which he had not the power to paſs over. I believe the like Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is no where to be found. They that favour the Glory of this High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Prince, are troubled that he ſhould loſe the Opportunity to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it. If <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler</hi> are ſo renowned, for the Conqueſts they made with a Detachment of a Detachment; how glorious might the Duke have been by the Atchievements of his whole Army? Fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men may do a great deal of ſuch Work, where five thouſand can do nothing. becauſe an equal Force (which is eaſily had) oppoſing them, will fruſtrate all their Attempts. But where five thouſand can do any thing, fifty thouſand will do ten times more, if there be ſo much to do.</p>
               <p>How did <hi>Hatwan</hi> (in particular) as it were invite the Duke to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege it, lying cloſe by him? Where he was not likely to find greater Reſiſtance, than <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler</hi> did afterward at <hi>Zolnock,</hi> a more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Place. By the taking of <hi>Hatwan,</hi> the Duke had been left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame for not repairing <hi>Vacia</hi> or <hi>Novigrad.</hi> ſince he had now a Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Town, to cover the Country which the Enemy had quitted, and to preſs upon the Country which the Enemy ſtill kept: which was the thing wanting in thoſe Parts. Alſo the Communication of <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Agria</hi> had been cut off, <hi>Hatwan</hi> lying between them.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant that a wiſe Reaſon is given, why the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> laying aſide at preſent the thoughts of theſe things, drew ſo ſoon into Winter Quarters. It is, that he might be the ſooner in the Field next year. But who knows what may happen, before the next year comes? Who knows how long the Pope will live, or whether another Pope will be ſo liberal? Who knows how long the King of <hi>Spain</hi> will live? Or how long the King of <hi>France</hi> will continue in this Mind? Or how long this League will laſt between the <hi>Germans, Poles,</hi> and <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans?</hi> Or how ſoon there may be ſome Accident, which may diſturb the Peace of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and by conſequence ſtop the progreſs of this War? Or whether the <hi>Turks</hi> will ever be again, in ſo bad a poſture to defend
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50124:20"/>themſelves? The Proverbial Advice, To make hay while the Sun ſhines, doth extend to all ſorts and conditions of People. Nor ſhould we leave any thing to be done to morrow, which may be done to day. The Duke had now a pretious Opportunity in his hands. The neglecting of one ſuch Opportunity, may turn the Fortune of Kingdoms and Empires. Such an Opportunity ought to be embraced and made uſe of, as if it were never to return again, nor any like it.</p>
               <p>The Succeſſes of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler</hi> (of which I have ſaid ſomething already, and muſt ſay more hereafter) do make it plainly appear; that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> had it been his hap to try it, might with eaſe have ſeized moſt of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Places on that ſide: and gone near to have clear'd the whole Country on the North of <hi>Danube,</hi> quite down to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade.</hi> But admitting he had found all the fortified Places impregnable, or at leaſt the attacking them not adviſable: yet by Marching in amongſt them, and eating up the open Country (as the <hi>French</hi> did in <hi>Flanders</hi>), he had done great Service. thereby maintaining his Army at his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Coſt, and depriving the Enemies Armies and Garriſons of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence. If an Army be but in the Enemies Country (which yet the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in this War ſeem induſtriouſly to avoid, or they have ſtrange ill luck at it), they are ſure to be doing one great part of their Work, and that is, devouring.</p>
               <p>Moreover though it ſhould be ſuppoſed, that this alſo could not be done, and that no Impreſſion of any kind could be made upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; yet ſome are of opinion, that the Duke had no need to ſpend his time in idle Encampings, and then run into Winter Quarters before Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſince he might have employed his Army to very good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. He might have laid a Bridge upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> ſomewhere near and above <hi>Buda,</hi> and cover'd it at each end with a ſtrong and large In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment: where a good part of his Army might have quartered all Winter. This Work had been both feaſible and profitable. To make it the more feaſible, the Duke had Veſſels, and a Bridge ready framed, which came down the River by him when he marched laſt againſt the Enemy. Alſo his Army was twice as ſtrong, as it was at the making of his laſt Bridge. And the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who had not hinder'd That, was no way likely to hinder This. He did not ſo much as Quarter againſt him or near him: within a while he drew off yet further, and lay quite below <hi>Buda:</hi> and a little after he marched clear away over the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck.</hi> The making of theſe Intrenchments I confeſs was a great Work. But there was the whole Army to do it; and ſuch things have been fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently done by leſs Armies. As for the Soldiers Lodgings who were here to Quarter, they might have made <hi>Baraques</hi> here, as we find they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50124:21"/>have been forced to do at <hi>Newhauſel.</hi> Alſo they might here have had Victuals and Forrage (as before hath been noted) almoſt as conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently as in <hi>Auſtria</hi> it ſelf, by reaſon of the eaſy Conveyance down the River<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſome they would have got out of the Country, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it far and wide. Then as to Profit and Advantage; This Bridge, with theſe Intrenchments, would have made large amends for the loſs of <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grad,</hi> for the not repairing of <hi>Vacia</hi> or <hi>Novigrad,</hi> and the not taking of <hi>Hatwan.</hi> ſince it had been better by many degrees, than all of them put together. And this Place, with the Force within it, would have cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all that large Tract of good Land lying behind it towards <hi>Gran:</hi> it would have driven the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Garriſons into corners, and harraſed all the open Country forward, almoſt as far as the <hi>Drave</hi> on the one ſide, and quite to the <hi>Teys</hi> on the other. It might have been the <hi>Maſtricht</hi> of <hi>Hungary:</hi> that is, might have done the <hi>Christians</hi> here as much ſervice, as <hi>Maſtricht</hi> did to the <hi>French</hi> while they held it. The <hi>Turks</hi> would have had a warm Winter on't, having ſuch a Fire in their Bowels. And <hi>Peſt</hi> and <hi>Buda, Hatwan, Agria,</hi> and <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> and their other Garriſons hereabouts, had been ſorely diſtreſſed this Winter for Victuals. We find they have much ado to ſubſiſt, though they have no Enemy near to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb or annoy them. Moreover the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by the help of this Bridge ſo fortified, would have been in a brave poſture to carry on the War next Spring. Theſe advantages the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> might have had, if they would have taken ſome pains to procure them. But it is too truly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of them, that in all this War they have been very ſparing of their labour. Whereas the <hi>Romans</hi> of old, and the <hi>French</hi> of late, have owed their Succeſſes as well to their hard Labour; as to their Money, their Skill, and their Valour.</p>
               <p>Before I leave this imaginary Bridge, I muſt anſwer an Objection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it: which is this. It is made a chief End of having here a great Strength of Men; that they might diſtreſs and ſtarve <hi>Buda,</hi> themſelves being the while ſupplied by the <hi>Danube.</hi> But ſince <hi>Buda</hi> ſtands upon the <hi>Danube</hi> likewiſe, why might it not be as well ſupplied the ſame way? I anſwer, that there is a very great and wide difference: in that Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt come up againſt the Stream to the <hi>Turks,</hi> whereas they fall down the Stream to the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Alſo the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Countries up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the River are much better cultivated, and can yield far greater Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Proviſions, than the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Countries upon the ſame River. And we ſee by Experience, that the <hi>Turks</hi> make but little uſe of this kind of Conveyance, in compariſon of the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> It is certainly a mighty Advantage to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Armies in <hi>Hungary,</hi> that not only the <hi>Danube,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Drave,</hi> the <hi>Save,</hi> and the <hi>Teys,</hi> bring them down all ſorts of Neceſſaries, out of the Emperour's Countries.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:50124:21"/>
               <p n="5">5. The burning of the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> was a fine Exploit perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Count <hi>Leſley:</hi> who hath deſervedly the reputation of one of the Emperour's beſt Commanders. But in the Conduct of this Affair, there are ſome things not eaſy to be apprehended. In the firſt place, it ſeems to have been carried with the leaſt ſecrecy, that ever any thing was. The Gazettes gave us advice (from <hi>Virovitza</hi>), what Count <hi>Leſley</hi> and his Council of War had reſolved upon. Which was, To go firſt to <hi>Caniza,</hi> and deſtroy the Country about it, thereby to incommode and diſtreſs that Garriſon; and then to march down to <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> with deſign to ruine that Bridge. And a week or a fortnight after, they tell us from the ſame place; That according to former reſolutions, Count <hi>Leſley</hi> had been at <hi>Caniza</hi> and done his work there, and was now marching to the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck.</hi> Who can deny but that this is fair open dealing, and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above-board? They let the World know what they intend to do, and they do it accordingly. In the next place, it is a wonder to ſome, that he did not keep the Town of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> when he had taken it. Though his Forces were not great, as not exceeding ſix thouſand Men, yet there was nothing that could diſturb or endanger him. For he had beaten the Enemy out of the Field; thoſe that eſcaped the Rout he gave them, being fled quite to <hi>Belgrade.</hi> And the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> was far off, and engaged againſt the Duke of <hi>Lorrain:</hi> and on the other ſide the <hi>Drave,</hi> over which he had no paſſage but by this Bridge. Moreover the making good this Town was a thing of mighty importance. For the <hi>Turks</hi> had been there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deprived of their only Paſs into Lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> and conſequently made incapable to defend it or maintain a War in it. In the third place, if the Town was not tenable, or (for Reaſons we are yet to learn) it was not adviſable to keep it, it is ſtill a wonder he did not do ſomething elſe. There was not a Man in the Field to oppoſe him. And the eaſy taking of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and of <hi>Michalowitz</hi> in his March thither, makes it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, how little difficulty he would have met with in other places, had he had the Heart to try them. Or he might have ſpent ſome time in fortifying and furniſhing that ſame <hi>Michalowitz.</hi> which (by <hi>De Witt</hi>'s particular Map of <hi>Hungary,</hi> for I find it in no other) lies commodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>Drave,</hi> about the half way between <hi>Virovitza</hi> and <hi>Eſſeck.</hi> [but I doubt they have quitted this Place, becauſe we hear no more of it.] Or at leaſt he might have Quarter'd upon the Enemy: all that noble Country between the <hi>Drave</hi> and <hi>Save</hi> being at his Command. and if he would be moving homeward, he might have done it by ſlow and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy Marches, and have grazed up the Country as he went. But inſtead of doing any of theſe things. the Count marched ſtraight away to <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovitza</hi> with all diligence. If a great Army of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50124:22"/>been at his heels, he could not have gone much faſter. Being thus got back into his own Quarters, and out of danger of being burdenſome to any but his Friends; he lay there very quietly and contentedly all the reſt of the Summer, and did juſt nothing.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It was by ſpecial Order from <hi>Vienna,</hi> that <hi>Newhauſel</hi> was reforti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Which makes ſome think that the great <hi>Walſtein</hi> was wiſe: who when he accepted the Supreme Command againſt the <hi>Swede,</hi> made it in his bargain (amongſt other things) that they ſhould ſend him no Orders from <hi>Vienna.</hi> for ſurely theſe Orders about <hi>Newhauſel</hi> ſeem much miſtaken. The Place was in a manner totally deſtroyed by the Siege. the Aſſailants had filled up a great part of the Ditch: the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part was beaten down by the Cannon: and the Bombs had ſo torn and ruin'd the Houſes, that only twelve of them were left ſtanding. Since therefore in effect it muſt be all new-built, it is to be conſider'd, whether the Situation did deſerve that Labour and Charge. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd that <hi>Newhauſel</hi> was a place important, when <hi>Comorra</hi> and It were the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Frontier on the North ſide the <hi>Danube,</hi> againſt <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Lewentz</hi> poſſeſſed by the <hi>Turks. Gran</hi> and <hi>Comorra</hi> ſtanding upon the River, and <hi>Lewentz</hi> and <hi>Newhauſel</hi> ten or twelve miles from it: and the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Towns being about thirty miles diſtant from the <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout twenty miles more backward the <hi>Turks</hi> had <hi>Novigrad</hi> and <hi>Vacia,</hi> ſtanding like the other: the firſt in the Upland, the laſt upon the River. and twenty miles yet farther back, they have <hi>Peſt, Hatwan,</hi> and <hi>Agria,</hi> all abreaſt: their Land on this ſide the <hi>Danube</hi> growing now broader. This was the poſture till about forty years ago; and then the <hi>Turks</hi> took <hi>Newhauſel.</hi> Whereupon the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to curb this Garriſon, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built <hi>Leopoldſtat,</hi> upon the River <hi>Waag;</hi> and they ſtrongly fortified <hi>Nitria,</hi> upon the ſame River on which <hi>Newhauſel</hi> ſtands. Alſo now lately, and after the Victory of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> took <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Lewentz:</hi> and (to come to the preſent time) this year they took <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel.</hi> Here it muſt plainly appear to any conſidering Perſon, that by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> having <hi>Lewentz</hi> and <hi>Gran, Newhauſel</hi> was become uſeleſs. And it became more uſeleſs by the <hi>Turks</hi> abandoning <hi>Novigrad</hi> and <hi>Vacia,</hi> which happened ſoon after. And it had become more uſeleſs yet, if the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had fortified <hi>Novigrad</hi> or <hi>Vacia,</hi> and had carried on the Frontier ſo far. [To ſay nothing of the Bridge upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> which I ſo much fancied in the lines fore-going.] A ſtrong Garriſon there, had covered all the Country behind it, and commanded a great way for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. But <hi>Newhauſel</hi> is now deep within the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Quarters, being almoſt ſeventy miles from any <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Garriſon. It doth not cover one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50124:22"/>ſoot of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Country, nor command one foot of the Enemies. Was it not therefore a ſtrange Reſolution, to beſtow nothing upon Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that had been highly uſeful; and to labour ſo much, upon a Place that is wholly uſeleſs? There was more need to ſlight two or three Garriſons about <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> than to make more. As things are now, there is not ſuch a Cluſter of Garriſons upon the face of the Earth. Here ſtands <hi>Newhauſel:</hi> and behind it <hi>Leopoldſtat</hi> within fifteen miles: on the left hand <hi>Nitria</hi> in the ſame diſtance: on the right hand <hi>Comor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> within ten miles, and <hi>Raab</hi> within ten miles more. Then before it (toward the <hi>Turks</hi>) are <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Lewentz</hi> within thirty miles. And theſe two laſt, which are neareſt the Enemy, are almoſt forty miles from any Garriſon they have. So that this multiplying of Garriſons, in this place, ſerves to ſmall purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The condition of Affairs is now ſuch, that the <hi>Turks</hi> are not likely ever to come ſo far as <hi>Newhauſel.</hi> And what if the Scene ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd? and the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould advance with a mighty Force this way? Were it better in this caſe, that <hi>Newhauſel</hi> lay raſed to the Ground, or were fortified as now it is, and had a Garriſon (as now it hath) of four thouſand Men? It ſeems very plain that it were better raſed to the Ground. For the Town might be well ſpared, there being more than enow hereabout beſides; and the Men might be made better uſe of, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Field, or for the reinforcement of the Neighbouring Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. A convenient number of Garriſons, well fortified and well mann'd, is certainly the beſt. Where they are too many, they cannot all be well mann'd: whereby ſome or other will become an eaſy Prey to the Enemy. But they may prove hard to be recover'd; and the Enemies neſtling and fixing in them may prove the deſtruction of the whole Country. So that too great a number is not only impertinent, but alſo dangerous and pernicious. If therefore a hundred ſtrong Holds could be had with a Wiſh in the <hi>Chriſtian Hungary,</hi> more than now are, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (we may preſume) enow already; the next Wiſh ſhould be to have them all demoliſh'd.</p>
               <p>That the Miſtake in fortifying <hi>Newhauſel</hi> may more plainly appear, I will make an Inſtance (by Suppoſition) in our own Country. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> were under two diſtinct Kings, as they are now happily united under One. The <hi>Scots</hi> take <hi>Barwick,</hi> and then they take <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> with all the Places between. And at laſt they take <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> alſo. to curb which laſt, as being the fartheſt advanced, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> make ſeveral ſtrong Garriſons near it. Afterwards the <hi>Engliſh</hi> retake <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> and all the other Places, <hi>Durham</hi> and <hi>Barwick</hi> excepted. At another time they likewiſe retake <hi>Durham:</hi> but having firſt ruin'd
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50124:23"/>it with their Bombs and Cannon. And hereupon the <hi>Scots</hi> demoliſh <hi>Barwick,</hi> and abandon it. Would not the World think us to be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mad, if we ſhould now refortify <hi>Durham</hi> with might and main, when it ſignifies nothing; and ſhould wholly neglect <hi>Barwick?</hi> It is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame caſe here. The <hi>Danube</hi> is their Sea: <hi>Vacia</hi> anſwers <hi>Barwick: Gran</hi> is <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> and <hi>Newhauſel</hi> is <hi>Durham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. We muſt believe General <hi>Schultz</hi> to be a Perſon of great Courage and Activity. One ſign of it is this; that he was always in the Field, and at work, ſome Weeks before other Men. Nevertheleſs he made no great progreſs: having to do with a tough Enemy, that held him hard to it. The Places that he beſieged, were defended with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Obſtinacy: Nor did Count <hi>Teckely</hi> fail on his part, to uſe unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried diligence in relieving them. At laſt by the taking of <hi>Eſperies,</hi> and the inveſting of <hi>Caſchaw</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Schultz</hi> ſeemed to have brought his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs into a very hopeful poſture. But now another is ſet over his head: and takes his work out of his hands. We cannot blame him for laying down his Command upon it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Count <hi>Caprara</hi> is the Man that now Commands at <hi>Caſchaw.</hi> He was firſt ſent to <hi>Agria</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> upon an unuſual Errand: which was, To take it (if he could) with Bombs. And this deſign was publiſh'd to the World, ſome time before it was put in Execution: for all the <hi>Gazettes</hi> had it. I think an Example will hardly be found, of a Town this way taken. Of a ſmall Caſtel perhaps there may. The <hi>French,</hi> 'tis true, have attacqued ſome Towns in this manner: as <hi>Oude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> by Land, and <hi>Genoa</hi> by Sea. But this was not with any hope or expectation to take the Places. The deſign therefore upon <hi>Agria</hi> was not like to ſucceed, and it ſucceeded not.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But <hi>Agria</hi> was only a thing by the by. and though it be one of the chief Fortreſſes of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, yet it was to be taken by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in their paſſage. We muſt therefore know, That this Force under <hi>Caprara</hi> was by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent chiefly againſt Count <hi>Tec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely.</hi> But how comes the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to concern himſelf thus with <hi>Teckely,</hi> who had <hi>Schultz</hi> upon him already? we thought the Duke had been engaged againſt the <hi>Seraſquier:</hi> and that the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> (with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces) was his Antagoniſt; with whom he was to cope, and to try Maſteries. And we expected, that ſince the Duke had already worſted him, he would never leave him off till either he had beaten him to pieces, or chas'd him out of <hi>Hungary.</hi> But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> it
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50124:23"/>ſeems, entertain'd no ſuch Thoughts: and all that little that he did was againſt <hi>Teckely.</hi> As if a Maſtiff, having a Bear by the Throat, ſhould let go his hold to ſnap at a Cur.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Though <hi>Caprara</hi> fail'd at <hi>Agria,</hi> yet at <hi>Caſchaw</hi> he had great Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: having that ſtrong Fortreſs yielded to him in a ſhort time. But for this he was beholden to <hi>Teckely</hi>'s ill Uſage by the <hi>Turks.</hi> Which was a ſtrange Hit to <hi>Caprara;</hi> and made thoſe things ſmooth and eaſy to him, which might otherwiſe have been exceeding difficult. For ſurely at the Surrender of <hi>Caſchaw,</hi> they were found ſo well provided at all points; that had it not been for <hi>Teckely</hi>'s Impriſonment, <hi>Caprara</hi> might have been as well repuls'd, as ever Man was.</p>
               <p n="11">11. When <hi>Caprara</hi> had made ſuch quick work at <hi>Caſchaw,</hi> it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that he would immediately have marched after <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſler,</hi> (who were now in the courſe of their Victories); or at leaſt have ſent them a good Reinforcement. Since the Nail did drive here ſo well, 'twas pity there ſhould want hands to ſtrike it. Theſe brave Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers wanted nothing but greater Forces, to make greater Conqueſts: thoſe they had with them, being hardly ſufficient to Man the Places they took. It had therefore been well done by <hi>Caprara,</hi> if he had ſent a good ſupply after them. But if he had gone himſelf, he had gain'd the Glory of the whole Action: as well of the things that had been done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his coming, as of thoſe that ſhould be done after. all would have been aſcribed to the General <hi>Caprara.</hi> But he ſeemed little to mind theſe Matters. All that he now did, was to ly hatching over his new Conqueſt of <hi>Caſchaw,</hi> and to put his Men in Winter Quarters. And this laſt he did ſooner then he needed, the Seaſon being yet favourable. For we find that <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler</hi> continued in Action, and in the Field, for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Weeks after <hi>Caſchaw</hi> was ſurrender'd.</p>
               <p n="12">12. It hath been ſaid before, that the Surrender of <hi>Caſchaw</hi> and other Places was occaſion'd by <hi>Teckely</hi>'s Impriſonment. And ſurely the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment of Count <hi>Teckely</hi> by the <hi>Turks,</hi> was a moſt horrid Act even amongſt <hi>Infidels.</hi> He fell by the Fraud of faithleſs Barbarians, to whom himſelf had been too faithful. But the <hi>Turks</hi> were ſufficiently puniſh'd for it: ſince it cauſed the Submiſſion of the revolted <hi>Hungarians</hi> to the Emperour, which to the <hi>Turks</hi> was one of the greateſt Blows they have receiv'd in all this War.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Among all the Champions engaged in this War of <hi>Hungary, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler</hi> have born away the prize. It muſt be confeſs'd they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50124:24"/>went about their Buſineſs like Workmen. Theſe are they that with a handful of Men, and when the year was almoſt quite ſpent: fell into the Enemies Country, and made very conſiderable Conqueſts. Which they have bravely maintain'd ever ſince: upon all Occaſions (and many ſuch Occaſions happen'd) beating and chaſing the Enemy. <hi>Heuſler</hi> had made himſelf famous before the Campagne began: and had given great proofs of his diligence and courage in hindering the Relief of <hi>Newhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</hi> for the effecting of which important Service the <hi>Turks</hi> made conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Attempts. He was almoſt all the Winter on Horſeback: while others were in there Stoves, at <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Inſpruck.</hi> And now, as <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prara</hi> had been detached from <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ſo <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tached from <hi>Caprara.</hi> and with their Party (for it may not be called an Army) they put themſelves upon Action, when the great ones were got into their Winter Quarters. They took <hi>Zolnock</hi> firſt, and afterward they took <hi>Saravas:</hi> both which are conſiderable Paſſes. the laſt upon the great River of <hi>Keroz,</hi> and the firſt upon the greater River of <hi>Teys.</hi> And the potent City of <hi>Debreczen,</hi> which before was neutral, they made to be wholly Imperial. They alſo took ſeveral other Places of leſs name, cleared a large Country, and pierced deep into the Enemies Quarters. They ſhewed what the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> might have done, if he had pleaſed with his whole Army to March that way. He might as eaſily have taken <hi>Waradine,</hi> and <hi>Segedine,</hi> and <hi>Temeſwar,</hi> as they took <hi>Saravas</hi> and <hi>Zolnock.</hi> He might have maſter'd the whole Country on this ſide the <hi>Danube,</hi> as eaſily as They did part. And as They Quarter'd their party upon the Enemy all Winter, ſo He might have done by his Army: not needing to ſend them ſo far as he did, ſome of them to the remoteſt parts of <hi>Germany.</hi> To make the thing ſhorter; if the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> after the Battel of <hi>Gran,</hi> had deliver'd his victorious Troops to <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler;</hi> we may well imagine what work they had made, and how like a Torrent they had born down all before them.</p>
               <p n="14">14. When the <hi>Venetians</hi> broke with the <hi>Turk,</hi> and joyn'd in the War againſt him; a Judgment might eaſily be from thence made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he was in a very ill Condition. For we might well think, that this wary People (who alſo have perfect Intelligence of the State of that Empire) would not engage but upon ſure terms. I believe this is the firſt time that they have been guilty of taking voluntary Arms againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi> they not being much given to that ſort of fooling, which ſome call Gallantry. This is not ſpoken in derogation of the <hi>Serene Republique.</hi> They deſerve great Honour upon ſeveral accounts. Nor ought we to heed the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter given them by <hi>Joſeph Scaliger,</hi> in his Invective Poem. Which I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50124:24"/>think is the bittereſt <hi>Satyr</hi> that ever was written, next to that of <hi>Catul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> againſt <hi>Caeſar.</hi> It ſeems the Pretenſions of this Family to <hi>Verona,</hi> had fill'd the Mans Pen with Gall and Vinegar.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> having thus undertaken the War, let us ſee how they proſecute it. Their <hi>Terra firma,</hi> or Land upon the Continent, lies round the bottom of their Gulf: within which, upon certain ſmall Iſlands, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> it ſelf is ſituate. Moſt of the Land by much, doth ly on the Weſtern ſide: and takes up a good part of <hi>Lombardy.</hi> The Eaſtern Extremity joyns upon <hi>Dalmatia:</hi> ſome of which Country they alſo have, the <hi>Turk</hi> poſſeſſing the greateſt part. and this is the only place, where they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon the <hi>Turks</hi> by land. Hither their Armies may march by land; or be tranſported croſs the Gulf, by a ſhort Cut and at an eaſy Charge. and here they might alſo be ſupplied at pleaſure. Moreover the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Dalmatia</hi> lies extended upon this Gulf of <hi>Venice,</hi> from <hi>Iſtria</hi> to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania,</hi> between three and four hundred miles in length: and it would be to the <hi>Venetians</hi> a thing of mighty importance to be ſole Maſters of it. It lies juſt at their doors: It would make their Dominion almoſt as weighty on this ſide of the Gulf as on the other: and it would eſtabliſh and ſecure their Soverainty over that Sea, ſomething better then their yearly m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrying their <hi>Doge</hi> to it. Of all the places in the World it lies moſt convenient for them. one foot of ground in <hi>Dalmatia</hi> is worth two or three elſewhere. And ſince the Enemy had likewiſe the <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Poles</hi> upon him, againſt whom his utmoſt Endeavours were required, and probably would be all too little; it could not otherwiſe be, but that <hi>Dalmatia</hi> would be very ſlenderly guarded. And it proved ſo in the Event: the <hi>Turks</hi> Forces there being inconſiderable.</p>
               <p>It was therefore with reaſon expected, that the <hi>Venetians</hi> would make it their principal Care, to get a good Army in <hi>Dalmatia.</hi> Which if they had done, it was hardly poſſible for them to fail of Succeſs. So that in all humane probability they might have made an eaſy Conqueſt of that whole Country. And then, their Forces being increaſed by the acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> there, and maintain'd in great meaſure by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try they had conquer'd; they might have carried the War into <hi>Albania,</hi> or <hi>Servia,</hi> or <hi>Boſnia:</hi> which border upon it, and would have been found as much unprovided. But in ſtead of this, they fall with might and main to Rigging out their Fleet, for which there was no occaſion: and they fill it with their Land Forces. As much neglecting <hi>Dalmatia</hi> out of Choice, as the <hi>Turks</hi> did out of Neceſſity. The <hi>Turks</hi> could not have a Force there, and it ſeems the <hi>Venetians</hi> would not. And the ſecond Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne was worſe then the firſt. For in the firſt they had there an Army, though it were ſmall and inconſiderable: but in the ſecond, they had none at all.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:50124:25"/>
               <p>And what did they do with their Fleet, in which we ſee was all their Confidence, and which took up all their Care? The firſt Summer was almoſt all ſpent in Preparations. At laſt they got to Sea: and took a ſmall Iſland, with a Fort near it upon the Main. And this was all they did that year: which did no way anſwer the Charge. The next year, as their Force was greater, ſo alſo they got out ſooner. And they carried their Army to the farther part of <hi>Morea,</hi> above a thouſand Miles from <hi>Venice.</hi> It cannot be denyed, but that they did their Work here very ſubſtantially and Soldier like. And they had as much Succeſs as could be expected from ſuch an Army. Which alſo was a good Army, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how far they were carried on Shipboard, and how great the Charge was of the Fleet that attended them. But here lies the Wonder, that they ſhould ſend an Army ſo far, when with the ſame Expence they might have had one in <hi>Dalmatia</hi> three or four times as big. as it is well known to thoſe, that know the Charge of a Fleet. What could they promiſe to themſelves in <hi>Morea,</hi> more than in <hi>Dalmatia?</hi> Did they hope to find them unprovided there, and a ſmall Force there to oppoſe them? they could not be worſe provided then in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> where there was no Force at all. Alſo the Places in <hi>Morea</hi> were as well fortified as in <hi>Dalmatia:</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were as likely to come into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, and revolt from the <hi>Turks,</hi> in the one Country as in the other. The Matter therefore in ſhort ſtands thus demonſtrable. Forty or fifty thouſand Men in <hi>Dalmatia</hi> could do much more then twelve or fifteen thouſand in <hi>Morea:</hi> But forty or fifty thouſand might as eaſily be had in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> as twelve or fifteen thouſand in <hi>Morea:</hi> Therefore it had plainly been more adviſable, to fall upon <hi>Dalmatia</hi> then <hi>Morea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For a further Illuſtration, let me make another Inſtance at home, and ſuppoſe once more that we had War with <hi>Scotland.</hi> In a time alſo when they were under great diſcouragement and diſorder, had other Enemies upon them, and were very weakly provided to defend themſelves. And We were willing to make the beſt uſe of ſuch an Opportunity. Would it not now be a rare Contrivance, if in ſtead of pouring a main Army into the South Parts of that Kingdom, which border upon us and ly open to us, we ſhould ſend a great Fleet with a ſmall Army, round by Sea to the fartheſt North? There to ly Hawking after Ports, when we might the while have been Conquering whole Countries. The Caſes are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly parallel: only with this difference, that whereas We ſhould have gone two or three hundred miles out of Our way, the <hi>Venetians</hi> have gone a thouſand out of Theirs. I might alſo inſtance in the <hi>French:</hi> and ſhew how contrary their Sentiments are to the <hi>Venetians</hi> in this matter. When They are minded to invade the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Kingdoms, they never
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50124:25"/>dream of carrying Armies by Sea, to <hi>Cales,</hi> or <hi>Gibraltore,</hi> or other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces remote; but fall directly into <hi>Catalonia</hi> or <hi>Biſcay.</hi> The <hi>Dutch,</hi> 'tis true, in the great War of the Confederates againſt the <hi>French;</hi> though they had work enough in <hi>Flanders,</hi> yet they ſent a Fleet with ſome Land-Men in it, to the farther parts of <hi>France.</hi> But they did this but once: they never thought fit to repeat it. Well perceiving, that the Money which ſuch a Fleet muſt coſt, would be much better beſtowed upon increaſing their Army in <hi>Flanders.</hi> Beſide, they did not deſign to make any great Conqueſts, or carry on a War at Land, as the <hi>Venetians</hi> do: but meerly to alarm and infeſt the Sea Coaſts. I cannot but obſerve by the by; that the <hi>Dutch</hi> did manage this Affair, in the Execution of it, as weakly, and awk wardly, and unskilfully, and unlearnedly, as ever did Men. I know this may ſeem incredible: but I could make it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particularly to appear, if it were not too long a digreſſion.</p>
               <p>It muſt be confeſs'd, that a Fleet and Army have notable Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by the Swiftneſs of their Motion: eſpecially where a large Sea-Coaſt lies expoſed to them. For it is impoſſible to hinder their Landing, as <hi>Rawleigh</hi> doth well demonſtrate. And before their Oppoſers can come up, they will for ſome time be Maſters of the Field: ſo as to be able to ravage the open Country, and likewiſe to poſſeſs themſelves of ſome Ports. which being relievable by Sea, will not eaſily be recover'd. By this way, he that is Maſter at Sea may put great hardſhips upon an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, that at Land is much ſtronger then himſelf. And wiſe Men are of opinion, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> might ſhrewdly trouble <hi>France</hi> this way, if a War ſhould happen. But the <hi>Venetians</hi> were now above theſe things: and had a better Game to play. A Country of the Enemies lay open to them, at their doors, and but weakly guarded, and joyning to them by Land. I think there cannot be ſtronger Invitations. What greater Advantage can be deſired, then to have a good Army in the Enemies Country, clearly Maſter of the Field? And this they might certainly have had, if they had employed their main Force upon <hi>Dalmatia.</hi> To be Maſter of the Field, though but for a time, is the End and Aim even of a deſultory Sea-War: as it hath been already noted. And ſurely if the temporary advantage be ſo deſirable, to have it conſtant and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent muſt be ſo much more. The <hi>Venetians</hi> moreover had not now a ſtronger Enemy to deal with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conſidering the Circumſtances he lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he was much weaker then themſelves. And therefore they had no need to run a Wild gooſe Chaſe, when they might carry their Buſineſs ſure before them, the plain way.</p>
               <p>It muſt alſo be confeſs'd, that it was neceſſary the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſhould have a Fleet at Sea. But a much leſs had been ſufficient. We find that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50124:26"/>the Fleet or Squadro, which <hi>Molino</hi> commanded in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> was more then the <hi>Turks</hi> could deal with.</p>
               <p>But here it will be objected, That the <hi>Venetians</hi> could not bring this great Army into <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> for want of Men to do it with. To this I anſwer; That the Money they ſpent in equipping and maintaining their great Fleets, would have drawn Men to them from all parts of <hi>Europe.</hi> And the fame of ſo hopeful and glorious an Expedition, would have rouſed up the moſt effeminate even of their own Subjects.</p>
               <p>It may be objected alſo, That regard muſt be had to the general In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Confederates. And this is beſt ſerved by giving the greateſt diverſion to the <hi>Turks.</hi> And the diverſion is greater by attacquing <hi>Morea,</hi> which is far from <hi>Hungary</hi> the chief Scene of Action; then by attacqu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> which is near it.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer; Firſt, that the greateſt Force makes the greateſt Diverſion: and therefore ſince there might be a much greater Force in <hi>Dalmatia</hi> then in <hi>Morea,</hi> the Diverſion would be much greater in <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia.</hi> Or according to what I ſaid before, forty or fifty thouſand Men in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> would give the <hi>Turks</hi> a greater Diverſion, then twelve or fifteen thouſand in <hi>Morea.</hi> Secondly, As I have ſaid upon another oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, that Diverſion is as good as Conjunction; ſo I ſay here and now, that Conjunction is as good as Diverſion: and therefore it cannot be hurtful, that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Armies be near one another. It is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of Confederates, that they all fall on where they can act with the greateſt Strength and Vigour. but whether near one another, or a great way off, is no way material. Thirdly, It is confeſs'd, that <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia</hi> being near to <hi>Hungary,</hi> if thoſe were the places chiefly attacqued, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Armies that defended them might relieve and aſſiſt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as there was occaſion. And would not the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Armies, that act in thoſe parts, have the ſame Convenience? Fourthly, It is confeſs'd likewiſe, that the <hi>Turks</hi> that defend <hi>Morea</hi> are quite divided from the reſt. but ſo alſo are the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that attacque it. If therefore we diſtract the Enemies Force by diſtracting our own, where lies the advantage? Fifthly, Herein the <hi>Turks</hi> had the advantage, that their Forces were found ready in <hi>Morea;</hi> which muſt have marched as far as <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> if that had been vigorouſly invaded. And ſo they were ſaved the labour of ſome Months, which that long March had required. Sixthly, If the beſt way of Diverſion be to go far off, then the farther the better. And therefore the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſhould have ſent their Fleet and Army, another thouſand Miles farther. which they might have done. <hi>Egypt</hi> or the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Land</hi> lay very fitly for their purpoſe: and this had been a rare Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50124:26"/>But if we will ſpeak ſeriouſly, no man can think that ſuch a Project had been adviſable.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee that the common Intereſt did not oblige the <hi>Venetians</hi> to go ſo far as <hi>Morea.</hi> And as for their own Intereſt, it plainly led them to <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> as the moſt commodious, which thing hath been noted before. It may now be added, that if they could get <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> they might keep it: but except the <hi>Turk</hi> be beaten out of <hi>Europe,</hi> he will find Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to beat the <hi>Venetians</hi> out of <hi>Morea.</hi> And in the mean time, let them do what they can, it will be a Charge and a Burden to them. whereas <hi>Dalmatia</hi> would maintain and defend it ſelf. 'Tis granted, that the Conqueſt of <hi>Morea</hi> would finely enlarge their Sea Dominion: but there is nothing like ſecuring their Gulf, which is done by the Conqueſt of <hi>Dalmatia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Admitting therefore that the attacquing of <hi>Morea</hi> were better for the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> and <hi>Poles,</hi> and would more facilitate their Conqueſts: yet clearly the <hi>Venetians</hi> are to do what is beſt for themſelves. They are not bound to be beating the Buſh, while others catch the Hare: nor to hold the Man's hands, while others rifle him: nor to be making Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, while others are making Conqueſts.</p>
               <p>They muſt not think that thoſe others, who have choſen the better part, will allow them any ſhare in Their Acquiſitions: nor muſt they reckon that they ſhall gain any more by the War, then what Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves get poſſeſs'd of.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Venetians,</hi> it is believed, have advanced more Money towards this War, ſince the time they engaged in it, then the Emperour hath done. And they might have had as good Armies at leaſt, and have been in a fair probability to make as great Conqueſts; had they not gone the wrong way to work, and begun at the wrong end. You will ſay the Emperour was vaſtly help'd by the <hi>Popes</hi> Money. But the <hi>Venetians</hi> might have had an equal ſhare with him, if they had made their bargain wiſely.</p>
               <p>They that would excuſe the <hi>Venetians</hi> Conduct, are ſtill of opinion, that they were obliged to it by Agreement with their Confederates. But we do not know this: nor is it to be preſumed. It being much more u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, that Confederates in theſe caſes be left at liberty, each to make the beſt of his own Game. But if there were ſuch an Agreement, it was their great Error to conſent to it.</p>
               <p>It hath been obſerved of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that they have a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular faculty of putting hard Conditions upon their Allies. But the <hi>Venetians</hi> were not now to be impoſed upon. For they came voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into a War, in which the others were engaged before: and therefore
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50124:27"/>might have had what terms they pleaſed. So that it was their own great fault if they were not good ones.</p>
               <p>It is the opinion of ſome Men; that the wiſe State of <hi>Venice,</hi> in this Affair, were over ſwayed by natural Inclination: which it is very hard to withſtand. They are much better provided for a War at Sea then at Land. which might make them apt to turn their Forces that way. We ſee all Creatures, by a certain Inſtinct, love to make uſe of that Part, which Nature hath moſt ſtrongly arm'd them withall. And the <hi>Venetians</hi> did now as naturally make uſe of their Fleet, as Bores uſe their Tusks, or Bulls uſe their Horns, or Horſes their Heels.</p>
               <p>I cannot leave the <hi>Venetians</hi> without one Remark more. It was much wonder'd, That when they had been victorious in <hi>Morea,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd Maſters of the Field, they yet carried their Army thence, to their own Neighbouring Iſlands for Winter Quarters. As if they had thought it a breach of good Manners, to quarter upon an Enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Or as if they had made <hi>Hungary</hi> their pattern: where all were highly Civil in this kind, two rude Fellows (<hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Heuſler</hi>) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. But what could the <hi>Venetians</hi> get by ſo doing? Certainly the Victuals which the Army conſumed in their Quarters, would have done as well if it had been brought to them at <hi>Morea.</hi> And why ſhould not the Victuals be carried to the Men, as well as the Men to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals? Moreover had the Army ſtaid here, if they could not have maintain'd themſelves wholly, they muſt have got ſomething towards their Maintenance. And the Winter in <hi>Morea</hi> is mild and gentle: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt Southern part of all the Continent of <hi>Europe.</hi> Alſo by their ſtay they had better protected the poor revolted <hi>Greeks:</hi> who contrariwiſe were in a very hard Condition, when they were abandon'd by their new Friends, and left to the rage of their old Maſters. And this, as the caſe here ſtands, is one great Evil of a deſultory Sea-War. The <hi>Greeks</hi> are ruin'd by the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> if they come not in to them; and by the <hi>Turks,</hi> if they do. Such a War being fit to infeſt and deſtroy, but not to protect.</p>
               <p>This ſending Men ſo far to Winter Quarters, ſeems to be a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. And ſo doth the proclaiming beforehand the time and place of Rendezvous. <hi>Caeſar</hi> was nine years in conquering <hi>Gaul:</hi> but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find that ever he did either of theſe things. If he had drawn back his Army every Winter, to Quarter in <hi>Italy;</hi> he might have been nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years about this Work, and left it undone at laſt. But his way was, to Quarter them in the midſt of their Buſineſs, and either upon his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, or as near them as he could, in ſeveral Camps which they ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intrenched. And when Spring came, he did not uſe to make a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50124:27"/>appointment of a Rendezvous; but by cloſe Orders, and without noiſe, he drew his Men together; and fell in among the Enemies, where he was leaſt expected, as ſudden as a Clap of Thunder. Commonly the firſt notice they had of him, was by ſeeing their Country in flames.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hath, of late years, given us a Pattern of a Rendezvous. and it was at the Siege of <hi>Bon.</hi> To which Place he made his Army march, from ſeveral Quarters and by ſeveral ways: none of them knowing or gueſſing, whither they were going or what they were to do, till they all met at one and the ſame time (their Marches being ſo admeaſur'd) under the Walls of the Town. We heard they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted the Place, before we heard that they were marching towards it; and we heard they had taken it, almoſt as ſoon as we heard that they were before it. This important Succeſs may juſtly be accounted the firſt ſtep of <hi>Holland</hi>'s deliverance from the <hi>French.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſhew the advantage yet further, of keeping an Army cloſe up upon the Enemy all Winter, if it may poſſibly be done; I ſhall here bring a domeſtique Example. though the memory of it I confeſs is not pleaſing. Our rebellious <hi>Rumpers</hi> got their Victory at <hi>Dunbar</hi> in Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember: after which they took in <hi>Edenburg, Lieth,</hi> and ſome other places; with the Countries on this ſide <hi>Sterling.</hi> and then the Winter came on. They now well ſaw, that theſe new Conqueſts would not be able to give Winter Quarters to their Army. But did they therefore draw them back into <hi>England?</hi> No, not a Man of them: they kept them all in <hi>Scotland.</hi> And moreover they were ſending them Recruits all Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: with the addition of divers new Regiments. Then for their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; they ſent them by Sea, both Victuals for their Men, and Hay for their Horſes. So that againſt Spring, their Army was more then doubled, upon the place, and ready for Action. Here now were Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that proſecuted their Buſineſs to the utmoſt. And ſurely without this vigorous Perſiſtance, they had not brought that Kingdom ſo ſoon under their Yoke; nor forced the King to that moſt Glorious, (but withal moſt hazardous, and only not fatal) March into <hi>England.</hi> To apply this Example, I do affirm; That the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Armies might as eaſily have been kept all Winter in <hi>Hungary</hi> or <hi>Morea,</hi> as the Blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army (ſo the <hi>Scots</hi> elegantly call'd it) was in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>The Magnanimous</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> is not to be blamed for the ſlack Proceedings of that Kingdom. but all the fault muſt be laid upon their unhappy Conſtitution: which ſeems to be meerly a tryal of Skill, how far Monarchy and Republique being mixed together, may ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and confound each other. And it is from the wretched defects
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50124:28"/>in their Government, that ſo mighty a Country makes ſo ſmall a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the World. This King, after the Relief of <hi>Vienna</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> (in which glorious Service he had a principal hand); and after the taking of <hi>Gran</hi> and ſome other Places; retired into his own Kingdom. the Quarters aſſign'd him in Upper <hi>Hungary</hi> being made too uneaſy by <hi>Teckely</hi>'s Garriſons. Now the <hi>Poles</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult how to proſecute the War. And ſince they joyn upon the <hi>Turk</hi> themſelves, they reſolve to employ their Forces upon their own Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier. Which ſurely was well conſider'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for now they might work for themſelves: whereas in <hi>Hungary</hi> they muſt work for another. And as to the Common Intereſt and Service, Diverſion and Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction are equipollent. or to ſpeak more at length, It doth as much good to divert the Enemy, as to joyn with the Friend.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> border upon the <hi>Poles</hi> in <hi>Moldavia:</hi> which is a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Country, but tributary to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and at their Command. being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Govern'd by a <hi>Vaivod</hi> or <hi>Hoſpodar,</hi> appointed by the Great <hi>Sultan.</hi> It was formerly dependent upon <hi>Poland:</hi> and it is divided from it by the River <hi>Nieſter.</hi> Into this fertile Country the <hi>Poles</hi> reſolve to March. where they could meet with little oppoſition; almoſt all the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Forces being drawn into <hi>Hungary.</hi> And we may be ſure the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Inhabitants were not unwilling to be freed from their Servitude: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if fair terms were offer'd them. But the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Levies and Recruits went on ſo exceeding ſlowly, that it was toward the end of September, before they got into the Field. And then they were about a Month in laying a Bridge over the <hi>Nieſter.</hi> So that by that time they were got into <hi>Moldavia,</hi> it was towards the end of October. And after they had been there ſome five or ſix days, without doing or attempting any thing; they found the Winter come on ſo faſt, that they concluded it their beſt way to March back into their Winter Quarters. And they did March back to their Winter Quarters accordingly. Was not this a moſt famous Expedition? We may defy all Places and Ages to ſhew the like. The next year they got ſooner into the Field, though not with ſo good an Army. But the <hi>Turks,</hi> having now recover'd their Spirits, brought ſuch a Force againſt them, and beſet them ſo cloſe, that they had much ado to make their Retreat.</p>
               <p>By what hath been here related and obſerv'd, it plainly appears; That the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> have loſt the greateſt Opportunity, that ever they had againſt the <hi>Turks.</hi> Theſe laſt, by the deſtruction of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at <hi>Vienna,</hi> were brought to ſuch a condition; that they were no way
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50124:28"/>able to reſiſt the united Powers of the <hi>Germans, Poles,</hi> and <hi>Venetians.</hi> Whoſe Force alſo was much increaſed by the great Sums of Money ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by the Pope. And the whole <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire was in a ſtrange Conſternation and Confuſion. But in this ſo favourable a Conjuncture; the <hi>Germans</hi> engaged themſelves before <hi>Buda,</hi> againſt Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, where they were held in Shackles: the <hi>Poles</hi> were aſleep, when they ſhould have been moſt active: and the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſpent their time and their Money, in rigging out a Fleet to no purpoſe, and then in play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at ſmall Game. Had the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> on all ſides, and with their whole Power, preſs'd briskly and vigorouſly upon the Enemy; it is probably believed, That the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> might (the very firſt year) have beaten them out of <hi>Hungary;</hi> the <hi>Venetians</hi> might have conquered <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and the adjoyning Countries: and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> might have ſeized <hi>Moldavia,</hi> together with <hi>Valachia</hi> which ſtood upon the ſame terms, and Marched to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
